<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="variants">
	<title>Variants</title> 
	<sect1>
		<title>What are variants?</title> 
		<para>MacPorts allows multiple versions of a port to be specified in a single Portfile. For example, vim can be built with and without x11 support. Rather than duplicate the whole port and have vim-x11 vim-nox ports MacPorts supports "variants". </para>

	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Guidelines</title>
		<para>There are some guidelines for using variants:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Never change the version of a port inside a variant.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Heavy usage of variants is considered bad style - keep the number of variants low.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Prefer function restricting variants over function enhancing ones. Make the default installation the one that serves most purposes.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Syntax</title> 
		<para>The variants syntax is largely identical to the syntax in the main part of the Portfile. </para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry id='variant'>
				<term>
					variant 
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The key variant is used to begin the foo variant as shown in the example. 
						<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
variant foo    { 
			      [variant code]
			      [more variant code]
                 }
]]> 
						</programlisting></para>

					<para>Within the variant block essentially all of the keys available in the main section are available. Using a key used in the main section will overwrite it. </para>

				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry id='append'>
				<term>
					append 
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>For most of the keys you can append additional terms. 
						<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
variant foo    { configure.args-append --with-x}

]]> 
						</programlisting></para>

				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry id='delete'>
				<term>
					delete 
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>For most of the keys you can delete terms. The item being deleted should match a string in the option being deleted exactly. 
						<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
variant gnome    { configure.args-delete --without-gnome}

]]> 
						</programlisting></para>

				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Advanced variants</title> 
		<para>For the most part, variants are quite straightforward to use. Several more advanced features of variants are also available. </para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry id='default_variants'>
				<term>
					default_variants 
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>In some cases you may want a variant or variants to be executed by default. For example w3m is distributed with a patch to add international text support. This is a vendor provided patch, but not a core part of the program. In this case it makes sense to make the internationalised version the default, but keep the vanilla w3m as the main port. The default_variants key is used in the main section of a Portfile, not in a variant. </para>

					<para><userinput>
							default_variants +foo +bar 
						</userinput></para>

				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry id='platform_variants'>
				<term>
					platform_variants 
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Platform specific variants are automatically executed on that platform, without needing any intervention from the user. Currently available platforms are: 
						<simplelist>
							<member>
								darwin
							</member>
							<member>
								freebsd
							</member>
							<member>
								linux
							</member>
						</simplelist></para>

					<para><userinput>
							variant foo darwin {[variant code]} 
						</userinput></para>

				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
