<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- -*- coding: utf-8; tab-width: 4; indent-tabs-mode: nil; c-basic-offset: 4 -*- vim:fenc=utf-8:et:sw=4:ts=4:sts=4:tw=120
-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY macports-version "2.3.4">
]>
<chapter id="installing">
    <title>Installing MacPorts</title>

    <para>This chapter shows you how to install MacPorts and its prerequisites step-by-step. Note that the section about
        <link linkend="installing.xcode">installing Xcode</link> is OS X-specific. If you wish to install MacPorts on
        another platform, first make sure you have a working C compiler installed, skip ahead to <link
            linkend="installing.macports.source">installing MacPorts from source</link>, and continue to the end of the
        chapter.</para>

    <section id="installing.xcode">
        <title>Install Xcode</title>

        <para><ulink url="https://developer.apple.com/xcode/">Xcode</ulink> is a package provided by Apple containing
            compilers, libraries and additional tools required to develop applications for OS X.</para>

        <note>
            <para>Always make sure to install the latest available version of Xcode for your OS X release; using
                outdated versions of Xcode may cause port install failures. Also note that Xcode is not updated via OS
                X's Software Update utility on OS versions prior to 10.6, and is updated via the Mac App Store starting
                with 10.7.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Follow the instructions for your version of OS X:</para>

        <section id="installing.xcode.mavericks">
            <title>Install Xcode on OS X 10.9 or Later</title>

            <para>Download the latest version of Xcode <ulink
                    url="https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action">from the Apple developer website</ulink> or
                get it <ulink url="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/xcode/id497799835">using the Mac App
                    Store</ulink>.</para>

            <para>Once you have Xcode installed, open a terminal, run <userinput>xcode-select --install</userinput>, and
                click the Install button to install the required command line developer tools. Don't worry if you see
                a message telling you the software cannot be installed because it is not currently available from the
                Software Update Server. This usually means you already have the latest version installed. You can also
                get the command line tools from <ulink url="https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action">the
                    Apple developer website</ulink>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.xcode.lion">
            <title>Install Xcode on OS X 10.7 Lion or OS X 10.8 Mountain Lion</title>

            <para>Download the latest version of Xcode <ulink
                    url="https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action">from the Apple developer website</ulink> or
                get it <ulink url="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/xcode/id497799835">using the Mac App
                    Store</ulink>.</para>

            <section id="installing.xcode.lion.43">
                <title>Xcode 4.3 and Later</title>

                <para>Xcode 4.3 and later do not automatically install the command line tools, but MacPorts requires
                    them. To install them, open the Xcode application, go to the Preferences window, to the Downloads
                    section, and click the Install button next to Command Line Tools. Be sure to return to this window
                    after every Xcode upgrade to ensure that the command line tools are also upgraded.</para>

                <para>If you wish to create Installer packages with <userinput>port pkg</userinput>, you will also need
                    to install PackageMaker, which is in the <quote>Auxiliary Tools for Xcode</quote> package as of
                    Xcode 4.3. The download page for this package can be opened via the Xcode -> Open Developer Tool ->
                    More Developer Tools... menu item. After downloading and mounting the disk image, drag the
                    PackageMaker application to your /Applications directory.</para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.xcode.snowleopard">
            <title>Install Xcode on Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard</title>

            <para>If you are using Mac OS X 10.6, there are two branches of Xcode which could be considered to be the
                latest, 3.2.x and 4.x. Xcode 4 costs money, but Xcode 3 is still available free of charge. There are two
                options for downloading it:</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Xcode 3.2 - smaller download, but you will need to run Software Update after installing to
                            get the latest version. Note that Apple might at some point discontinue providing these
                            updates via their update servers.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Xcode 3.2.6 and iOS SDK 4.3 - includes the iOS SDK which is not needed for
                            MacPorts.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>Both are available from the <ulink url="https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action">Apple
                    developer website</ulink>. You may also be able to install Xcode 3.2 from your Mac OS X 10.6 DVD and
                then run Software Update to get the latest version.</para>

            <para>Ensure that those of the following options that are available in the installer for your version of
                Xcode are selected:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>UNIX Development</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>System Tools</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>X11 SDK</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>Command Line Support</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.xcode.other">
            <title>Install Xcode on Older Releases of Mac OS X</title>

            <para>If you have an earlier release of Mac OS X, you may download the latest version of Xcode for OS X 10.5
                (Xcode 3.0 and Xcode 3.1 Developer Tools) or 10.4 (Xcode 2.4.1 and Xcode 2.5 Developer Tools) from the
                <ulink url="https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action">Apple developer website</ulink>.</para>

            <para>Ensure that those of the following options that are available in the installer for your version of
                Xcode are selected:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>UNIX Development</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>System Tools</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>X11 SDK</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guibutton>Command Line Support</guibutton></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="installing.macports">
        <title>Install MacPorts</title>

        <para>If you are using OS X, you should install MacPorts using the OS X package installer unless you do not wish
            to install it to <filename>/opt/local/</filename>, the default MacPorts location, or if you wish to install
            a pre-release version of MacPorts base. However, if you wish to <link
                linkend="installing.macports.source.multiple">install multiple copies of MacPorts</link> or install
            MacPorts on another OS platform, you must <link linkend="installing.macports.source">install MacPorts from
                the source code</link>.</para>

        <note>
            <para>Though a distinction is made between pre-release and release versions of MacPorts base, the ports
                collection supports no such distinction or versioning. The <link
                    linkend="using.port.selfupdate">selfupdate</link> command installs the latest port revisions from
                Subversion (at a slight delay), and updates MacPorts base to the latest released version.</para>
        </note>

        <section id="installing.macports.binary">
            <title>OS X Package Install</title>

            <para>The OS X package installer automatically installs MacPorts, <link linkend="installing.shell">sets the
                    shell environment</link>, and runs a <link linkend="using.port.selfupdate">selfupdate</link>
                operation to update the ports tree and MacPorts base with the latest release.</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Download the latest
                        <filename>MacPorts-&macports-version;-<replaceable>....</replaceable>pkg</filename> installer from the
                        <ulink url="https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/">MacPorts download directory</ulink>. Here
                        are direct links for the latest versions of OS X:</para>

                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>
                                OS X 10.10 Yosemite:
                            </term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><ulink url="https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/MacPorts-&macports-version;-10.10-Yosemite.pkg">MacPorts-&macports-version;-10.10-Yosemite.pkg</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>
                                OS X 10.9 Mavericks:
                            </term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><ulink url="https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/MacPorts-&macports-version;-10.9-Mavericks.pkg">MacPorts-&macports-version;-10.9-Mavericks.pkg</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>
                                OS X 10.8 Mountain Lion:
                            </term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><ulink url="https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/MacPorts-&macports-version;-10.8-MountainLion.pkg">MacPorts-&macports-version;-10.8-MountainLion.pkg</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Double-click the downloaded package installer to perform the default <quote>easy</quote>
                        install.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>After this step you are done already, MacPorts is now installed and your shell environment was
                        set up automatically by the installer. To confirm the installation is working as expected, now
                        try using <command>port</command> in a <emphasis>new</emphasis> terminal
                        window.</para>

                    <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>port version</userinput></programlisting>
                    <screen>Version: &macports-version;</screen>

                    <para>In case of problems such as <quote>command not found</quote>, make sure that you opened a new
                        terminal window or consult <xref linkend="installing.shell"/>. Otherwise, please skip the
                        remainder of this chapter and continue with <xref linkend="using"/> in this guide.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.macports.source">
            <title>Source Install</title>

            <para>If you installed MacPorts using the package installer, skip this section. To install MacPorts from the
                source code, follow the steps below.</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Download and extract the <ulink
                            url="https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/MacPorts-&macports-version;.tar.bz2"> MacPorts
                            &macports-version; tarball</ulink>. Either do so using your browser and the Finder, or use
                        the given commands in a terminal window.</para>

                    <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl -O https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/MacPorts-&macports-version;.tar.bz2</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tar xf MacPorts-&macports-version;.tar.bz2</userinput></programlisting>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Afterwards, perform the commands shown in the terminal window. If you wish to use a path other
                        than <filename>/opt/local</filename>, follow the instructions for <link
                            linkend="installing.macports.source.multiple">installing multiple copies of MacPorts</link>
                        instead.</para>

                    <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd MacPorts-&macports-version;/</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>./configure</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo make install</userinput></programlisting>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Please continue with <xref linkend="installing.shell" /> to set up your shell
                        environment.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.macports.subversion">
            <title>Subversion Install</title>

            <para>If you installed MacPorts using the package installer, skip this section.</para>

            <para>There are times when some may want to run MacPorts from a version newer than the current stable
                release. Maybe there's a new feature that you'd like to use, or it fixes an issue you've encountered, or
                you just like to be on the cutting edge. These steps explain how to run completely from trunk, using
                only Subversion to keep MacPorts up to date.</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Check out MacPorts source</para>

                    <para>Pick a location to store a working copy of the MacPorts code. For this example,
                        <filename>/opt/mports</filename> will be used, but you can put the source anywhere. This example
                        will create <filename>/opt/mports/trunk</filename> containing everything needed for
                        MacPorts.</para>

                    <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mkdir -p /opt/mports</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd /opt/mports</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>svn checkout https://svn.macports.org/repository/macports/trunk</userinput></programlisting>

                    <note>
                        <para>You only really need the base subdirectory to run MacPorts, so you can avoid checking out
                            the rest if you don't want to use a Subversion-based ports tree (see Step 3 below). To just
                            get the base directory, append <filename>/base</filename> to the end of the svn checkout
                            command above. The resulting directory will then be
                            <filename>/opt/mports/base</filename>.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Build and Install MacPorts</para>

                    <para>MacPorts uses autoconf and makefiles for installation. These commands will build and install
                        MacPorts to <filename>/opt/local</filename>. You can add <option>--prefix</option> to
                        <filename>./configure</filename> to relocate MacPorts to another directory if needed.</para>

                    <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd /opt/mports/trunk/base</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>./configure --enable-readline</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo make install</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make distclean</userinput></programlisting>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>(Optional) Configure MacPorts to use port information from Subversion</para>

                    <para>This step is useful if you want to do port development. Open
                        <filename>/opt/local/etc/macports/sources.conf</filename> in a text editor. The last line which
                        should look like this:</para>

                    <programlisting>rsync://rsync.macports.org/release/tarballs/ports.tar [default]</programlisting>

                    <para>Change it to point to the working copy you checked out:</para>

                    <programlisting>file:///opt/mports/trunk/dports [default]</programlisting>

                    <para>Now MacPorts will look for portfiles in the working copy and use Subversion instead of rsync
                        to update your ports tree.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Environment</para>

                    <para>You should setup your PATH and other environment options according to <xref
                        linkend="installing.shell" />.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.macports.source.multiple">
            <title>Install Multiple MacPorts Copies</title>

            <para>Occasionally a MacPorts developer may wish to install more than one MacPorts instance on the same
                host. Only one copy of MacPorts may use the default prefix <filename>/opt/local</filename>, so for
                additional installations use the option <option>--prefix</option> as shown below. It's also recommended
                to change the applications dir using <option>--with-applications-dir</option> to avoid conflicts in
                <filename>/Applications/MacPorts</filename>.</para>

            <note>
                <para>The first command temporarily removes the standard MacPorts binary paths because they must not be
                    present while installing a second instance.</para>
            </note>

            <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export PATH=/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>MP_PREFIX=/opt/macports-test</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>./configure --prefix=$MP_PREFIX --with-applications-dir=$MP_PREFIX/Applications</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make</userinput>
<!--                --><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo make install</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>After installing the second instance you might need to add
                <programlisting>startupitem_install no</programlisting>
                to <filename>$MP_PREFIX/etc/macports/macports.conf</filename> to avoid conflicts in
                <filename>/Library/LaunchAgents</filename>.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="installing.macports.upgrade">
        <title>MacPorts Upgrade</title>

        <para>MacPorts base upgrades are performed automatically (when a newer release is available) during a <link
                linkend="using.port.selfupdate">selfupdate</link> operation. To upgrade a copy of MacPorts that was
            installed from source to the newer release of the source code, simply repeat the <link
                linkend="installing.macports.source">source install</link> with the newer version of the MacPorts source
            code.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="installing.macports.uninstalling">
        <title>Uninstall</title>

        <para>Uninstalling MacPorts can be a drastic step, and depending on the issue you are experiencing, you may not
            need to do so. If you are unsure, ask on the <ulink
                url="http://lists.macosforge.org/mailman/listinfo/macports-users">macports-users</ulink> mailing list
            first.</para>

        <para>If you need to uninstall MacPorts, and <command>port</command> is functioning, first
        uninstall all the installed ports by running this command in the Terminal:</para>

        <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo port -fp uninstall installed</userinput></programlisting>

        <para>All that will be left in your installation prefix now will be files that were not registered to any port.
            This includes configuration files, databases, any files which MacPorts renamed in order to allow a forced
            installation or upgrade, and the base MacPorts software itself. You may wish to save your configuration
            files (most are in <filename>$prefix/etc</filename>), databases, or any other unique data by moving it
            aside.</para>

        <para>To remove all remaining traces of MacPorts, run the following command in the Terminal. If you have changed
            <varname>prefix</varname>, <varname>applications_dir</varname> or <varname>frameworks_dir</varname> from
            their default values, then replace <filename>/opt/local</filename> with your <varname>prefix</varname>,
            replace <filename>/Applications/MacPorts</filename> with your <varname>applications_dir</varname>, and/or
            add your <varname>frameworks_dir</varname> to the list, respectively.</para>

        <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo rm -rf \
        /opt/local \
        /Applications/DarwinPorts \
        /Applications/MacPorts \
        /Library/LaunchDaemons/org.macports.* \
        /Library/Receipts/DarwinPorts*.pkg \
        /Library/Receipts/MacPorts*.pkg \
        /Library/StartupItems/DarwinPortsStartup \
        /Library/Tcl/darwinports1.0 \
        /Library/Tcl/macports1.0 \
        ~/.macports</userinput></programlisting>

        <para>If you use a shell other than bash (perhaps tcsh), you may need to adjust the above to fit your shell's
            syntax. Also note that depending on which version of MacPorts you have and which ports you have installed,
            not all of the above paths will exist on your system. This is OK.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="installing.shell">
        <title>MacPorts and the Shell</title>

        <para>MacPorts requires that some environment variables be set in the shell. When MacPorts is installed using
            the OS X package installer, a <quote>postflight</quote> script is run after installation that automatically
            adds or modifies a shell configuration file in your home directory, ensuring that it defines variables
            according to the rules described in the following section. Those <link
                linkend="installing.macports.source">installing MacPorts from source code</link> must modify their
            environment manually using the rules as a guide.</para>

        <para>Depending on your shell and which configuration files already exist, the installer may use
            <filename>.profile</filename>, <filename>.bash_login</filename>, <filename>.bash_profile</filename>,
            <filename>.tcshrc</filename>, or <filename>.cshrc</filename>.</para>

        <section id="installing.shell.postflight">
            <title>The Postflight Script</title>

            <para>The postflight script automatically sets the <varname>PATH</varname> variable, and optionally the
                <varname>MANPATH</varname> and <varname>DISPLAY</varname> variables according to the rules described
                below. If a current shell configuration file exists at installation time it is renamed to
                <quote>mpsaved_$timestamp</quote>. Those <link linkend="installing.macports.source">installing MacPorts
                    from source code</link> must modify their environment manually using the rules as a guide.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Required: <varname>PATH</varname> variable</para>

                    <para>This variable is set by the postflight script to append the MacPorts executable paths to the
                        default path as shown. The MacPorts paths are appended at the front of <varname>PATH</varname>
                        so the MacPorts libraries will take precedence over vendor-supplied libraries for ported
                        software at runtime.</para>

                    <programlisting>export PATH=/opt/local/bin:/opt/local/sbin:$PATH</programlisting>

                    <note>
                        <para>The user environment's $PATH is not in effect while ports are being installed, because the
                            $PATH is scrubbed before ports are installed, and restored afterwards. To change the search
                            path for locating system executables (rsync, tar, etc.) during port installation, see the
                            <link linkend="internals.configuration-files.macports-conf">macports.conf</link> file
                            variable <varname>binpath</varname>. But changing this variable is for advanced users only,
                            and is not generally needed or recommended.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Optional: <varname>MANPATH</varname> variable</para>

                    <para>Condition: If prior to MacPorts installation a <varname>MANPATH</varname> variable exists in
                        a current <filename>.profile</filename> that contains neither the value
                        <filename>${prefix}/share/man,</filename> nor any empty values, the postflight script sets the
                        <varname>MANPATH</varname> variable as shown below. Otherwise, the <varname>MANPATH</varname>
                        variable is omitted.</para>

                    <programlisting>export MANPATH=/opt/local/share/man:$MANPATH</programlisting>

                    <para>Here are some examples of paths that contain empty values:</para>

                    <simplelist>
                        <member>/usr/share/man:</member>
                        <member>:/usr/share/man</member>
                        <member>/usr/share/man::/usr/X11R6/man</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Optional: <varname>DISPLAY</varname> variable</para>

                    <para>Condition: If installing on a Mac OS X version earlier than 10.5 (Leopard), and if a shell
                        configuration file exists at time of MacPorts installation without a <varname>DISPLAY</varname>
                        variable, the postflight script sets a <varname>DISPLAY</varname> variable as shown below. The
                        <varname>DISPLAY</varname> variable is always omitted on Mac OS X 10.5 or higher.</para>

                    <programlisting>export DISPLAY=:0.0</programlisting>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.shell.verifyprofile">
            <title>Verify the Configuration File</title>

            <para>To verify that the file containing the MacPorts variables is in effect, type <command>env</command> in
                the terminal to verify the current environment settings after the file has been created. Example output
                for <command>env</command> is shown below.</para>

            <note>
                <para>Changes to shell configuration files do not take effect until a new terminal session is
                    opened.</para>
            </note>

            <screen>MANPATH=
<!--        -->TERM_PROGRAM=Apple_Terminal
<!--        -->TERM=xterm-color
<!--        -->SHELL=/bin/bash
<!--        -->TERM_PROGRAM_VERSION=237
<!--        -->USER=joebob
<!--        -->__CF_USER_TEXT_ENCODING=0x1FC:0:0
<!--        -->PATH=/opt/local/bin:/opt/local/sbin:/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin
<!--        -->PWD=/Users/joebob
<!--        -->EDITOR=/usr/bin/pico
<!--        -->SHLVL=1
<!--        -->HOME=/Users/joebob
<!--        -->LOGNAME=joebob
<!--        -->DISPLAY=:0.0
<!--        -->SECURITYSESSIONID=b0cea0
<!--        -->_=/usr/bin/env</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="installing.shell.editorvar">
            <title>Optional Editor Variables</title>

            <para>You can set an environment variable in order to use your favorite text editor with edit option of port
                command.</para> <para>MacPorts will check <varname>MP_EDITOR</varname>, <varname>VISUAL</varname> and
                <varname>EDITOR</varname> in this order, allowing you to either use a default editor shared with other
                programs (<varname>VISUAL</varname> and <varname>EDITOR</varname>) or a Macports' specific one
                (<varname>MP_EDITOR</varname>).</para>

            <para>For example, to use the nano editor, add this line to your bash config:</para>

            <programlisting>export EDITOR=/usr/bin/nano</programlisting>

            <para>To use the user-friendly GUI editor <ulink
                    url="http://www.barebones.com/products/textwrangler/">TextWrangler</ulink> (installation required),
                add this line:</para>

            <programlisting>export EDITOR=/usr/bin/edit</programlisting>

            <para>To keep a command-line text editor as default while using a graphic editor with portfiles, add
                this:</para>

            <programlisting>export EDITOR=/usr/bin/vi
<!--        -->export MP_EDITOR=/usr/bin/edit</programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
