<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>MacPorts is an easy to use system for compiling, installing, and
  managing open source software. MacPorts may be conceptually divided into two
  main parts: the infrastructure, known as MacPorts base, and the set of
  available ports. A MacPorts port is a set of specifications contained in a
  <link linkend="development.introduction">Portfile</link> that defines an
  application, its characteristics, and any files or special instructions
  required to install it. This allows you to use a single command to tell
  MacPorts to automatically download, compile, and install applications and
  libraries. But using MacPorts to manage your open source software provides
  several other significant advantages. For example, MacPorts:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Installs automatically any required support software, known as
      <link linkend="reference.dependencies">dependencies</link>, for a given
      port.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Provides for uninstalls and upgrades for installed ports.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Confines ported software to a private <quote>sandbox</quote> that
      keeps it from intermingling with your operating system and its
      vendor-supplied software to prevent them from becoming corrupted.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Allows you to create pre-compiled binary installers of ported
      applications to quickly install software on remote computers without
      compiling from source code.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>MacPorts is developed on Mac OS X, though it is designed to be
  portable so it can work on other Unix-like systems, especially those
  descended from the Berkeley Software Distribution (BSD).</para>

  <para>The following notational conventions are used in the MacPorts Guide to
  distinguish between terminal input/output, file text, and other special text
  types.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Terminal I/O and file text.</para>

      <programlisting><prompt>%% </prompt><userinput>Commands to be typed into a terminal window.</userinput></programlisting>

      <screen>Command output to a terminal window.</screen>

      <programlisting>File text.</programlisting>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Other special text types.</para>

      <para>A hyperlink: <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spontaneous_combustion">spontaneous
      combustion</ulink>.</para>

      <para>A file: <filename>/var/log/system.log</filename>.</para>

      <para>A command: <command>ifconfig</command>.</para>

      <para>An option: port <option>install</option></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</chapter>