<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="reference.dependencies">
  <title>Dependencies</title>

  <para>Free and open source software is highly modular, and MacPorts ports
  often require that other ports be installed beforehand; these
  prerequisites for a given port are called a port's
  <quote>dependencies</quote>.</para>

  <para>There are three types of MacPorts dependencies: library, build, and
  run dependencies. Dependency types are important for proper port upgrade
  and uninstall behavior. For example, you may not uninstall a port that is
  a library dependency for another port, though you may remove one with a
  build dependency; likewise, upgrading a port will upgrade its library and
  build dependencies also, but not its run dependencies.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_lib</term>

      <term>depends_lib-append</term>

      <term>depends_lib-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>configure</option>, <option>build</option>,
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Library dependencies are needed both at
        build time (for headers and libraries to link against) and at run
        time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_build</term>

      <term>depends_build-append</term>

      <term>depends_build-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>build</option>, <option>destroot</option>,
        <option>install</option>, and <option>package</option>. Build
        dependencies are needed when software is compiled, but not needed at
        all once the software is compiled and installed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_run</term>

      <term>depends_run-append</term>

      <term>depends_run-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Run dependencies are needed when the
        software is run, but not to compile it.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <section id="reference.dependencies.types">
    <title>Port and Non-Port Dependencies</title>

    <para>Port dependencies should be provided by MacPorts ports whenever
    possible, however dependencies may be provided by vendor-supplied
    software when satisfying a dependency by a port is not practical or
    desirable for a special reason. Dependencies of this type are called
    non-port dependencies.</para>

    <para>Non-port dependencies should only be used if the application or
    library can be installed by multiple ports (for example stable and
    -devel version) or if it can't be installed with MacPorts.</para>

    <para>Port dependencies, the preferred type, are specified as shown in
    these examples:</para>

    <programlisting>depends_lib         port:rrdtool port:apache2

depends_build       port:libtool

depends_run         port:apache2 port:php5</programlisting>

    <para>Non-port dependencies are specified as shown in these
    examples:</para>

    <programlisting>depends_lib         lib:libX11.6:xorg

depends_build       bin:glibtool:libtool

depends_run         path:${prefix}/lib/libltdl.a:libtool</programlisting>
  </section>
</section>
