<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="reference.variants">
  <title>Variants</title>

  <para>MacPorts variants are conditional modifications of port installation
  behavior that may be invoked by a user at the time of port install.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>variant [requires variant] [conflicts variant] [description
      description]</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The variant declaration may contain any keywords that can be
        placed in a Portfile's global section. If you wish to execute system
        (shell) calls or Tcl extensions during the execution of a port
        phase, you should place those statements within a
        <literal>variant_isset</literal> conditional within a phase
        declaration and not within the variant declaration itself.
        Dependencies and conflicts with other variants in the same port can
        be expressed with requires and conflicts. See the isset Tcl
        extension.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Default: no</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Example:</para>

            <programlisting>variant gnome requires glib {
    configure.args-append   --with-gnome
    depends_lib-append      port:gnome-session
}</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>default_variants</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>If variants are defined, then the default_variants value lists
        which variants are enabled by default. This allows for Portfile
        modularity and also allows users to suppress default variants if
        they wish.</para>

        <para>Due to a bug in the current Macports base default_variants
        shouldn't be used at the moment as they cause problems while
        upgrading ports.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Default: none</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Example:</para>

            <programlisting>default_variants    +ssl +tcpd

</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Default variants may be suppressed by preceding a variant name
        with a "-" as shown in this example.</para>

        <programlisting><prompt>%%</prompt> <userinput>port install foo -ssl</userinput></programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>universal_variant</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>When using MacPorts on Mac OS X, a universal variant is
        defined by default to configure ports with universal flags. The
        variant can be overridden if the default code does not work (see the
        Configure Universal section below), or suppressed if a universal
        variant is not possible for the port with this keyword.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Default: yes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Example:</para>

            <programlisting>universal_variant   no</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>
