<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="reference.keywords">
  <title>Global Keywords</title>

  <para>MacPorts keywords are used to specify required or optional items
  within a Portfile, or to override default options used by MacPorts base for
  individual ports. Keywords are to be used within the <quote>global</quote>
  and <quote>variant</quote> sections of Portfiles, and not within optional
  port phase declarations.</para>

  <para>The global keywords listed below specify information for ports as a
  whole, whereas the keywords listed under a port phase specify information to
  be used during a particular installation phase.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>PortSystem</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The first non-comment line of every Portfile; it should be
        followed by PortGroup inclusions (if any) and then a blank line.
        It defines which version of the Portfile interpreter will be used.
        (There is currently only one version.)</para>

        <programlisting>PortSystem          1.0

</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>name</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The name of the port. To avoid special interpretation by shells
        and the like, names should contain only alphanumeric characters,
        underscores, dashes or dots. For projects whose proper names contain
        <quote>+</quote> characters, change these to <quote>x</quote> (i.e.
        <quote>libstdc++</quote> becomes <quote>libstdcxx</quote>).</para>

        <programlisting>name                foo</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>version</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The version of the ported software.</para>

        <programlisting>version             1.23.45</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>revision</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Optional keyword (default is 0) that is used to track port
        revisions. It should not be incremented for port revisions unless it
        would benefit users to upgrade an installed port, and cleared when the
        port is updated to a newer version.</para>

        <para>It should be used if a bug in the Portfile was found and all
        installations of this port have to be updated. If the change only
        affects new installations, there is no need to increase it.</para>

        <programlisting>revision            1</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>epoch</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An optional keyword (default value is 0) that must be used when
        a port is updated to a version that is numerically less than the
        previous version, for example 1.10 -&gt; 1.2 or 20070928 -&gt; 1.0.
        Some Portfile authors have used large epoch values that look like a
        date, but there is no reason to do so. The epoch is simply an unsigned
        integer, and the only requirement is that it never be decreased.</para>

        <programlisting>epoch               1</programlisting>

        <note>
          <para>An epoch is not needed for most ports. If a port's version
          numbers advance in normal dotted-decimal sequence, there is no reason
          to add an epoch.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>categories</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The category under which the ported software falls. The first
        category should be the same as the directory within which the Portfile
        is stored; secondary and tertiary categories may be selected.</para>

        <programlisting>categories          net security</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry id="reference.keywords.maintainers">
      <term>maintainers</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A port's maintainers are the people who have agreed to take
        responsibility for keeping the port up-to-date. Most ports have only a
        single maintainer, but some ports have two or more comaintainers. The
        <literal>maintainers</literal> keyword lists the maintainers' email
        addresses, preferrably in the obfuscated form which hides them
        from spambots:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>For addresses in domain @macports.org, simply omit the
            domain name.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For addresses in other domains, e.g.
            <email>account@example.org</email>, use the convention
            example.org:account to specify the address.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In the example below, the maintainer email addresses
        <email>jdoe@macports.org</email> and
        <email>julesverne@example.org</email> are hidden using these
        conventions.</para>

        <programlisting>maintainers         jdoe \
                    example.org:julesverne</programlisting>

        <note>
          <para>The address <email>nomaintainer</email> designates a port that
          is not maintained by anybody and may be modified by any committer.
          Feel free to claim maintainership of a nomaintainer port if desired.
          The address <email>openmaintainer</email> designates a port that has
          a maintainer who allows minor changes to be committed without his or
          her prior approval. Port maintainers who are not committers are
          encouraged to add <email>openmaintainer</email> to their ports.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>description</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A one-sentence description of the ported software.</para>

        <programlisting>description         A classic shooter arcade game.</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>long_description</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A long description of the ported software. Break long lines with
        escaped newlines.</para>

        <programlisting>long_description    A classic shooter arcade game derived from \
                    the game alien-munchers.  Not suitable for \
                    children under two years old.</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>homepage</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Port application's homepage.</para>

        <programlisting>homepage            http://www.example.org/apps</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>platforms</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The platforms on which the port has been tested.</para>

        <!-- TODO: add possible values -->

        <programlisting>platforms           darwin freebsd</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>supported_archs</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The CPU architectures for which this port can be built. Archs currently
        supported by Mac OS X are: i386, ppc, ppc64, x86_64. If this option is not
        set, it is assumed that the port can build for all archs. If a port does not
        install any architecture-specific files, use the special value
        <option>noarch</option>.</para>

        <para>If the building architecture isn't among supported_archs, port
        fails with an error message, except when building on x86_64 and
        supported_archs contains i386 or when building on ppc64 and
        supported_archs contains ppc, in which case the port will be built in
        32-bit mode.</para>

        <programlisting>supported_archs           i386 ppc</programlisting>
        <programlisting>supported_archs           noarch</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>license</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The proper format for license consists of the license name,
        followed by a hyphen and number if indicating a specific version. A
        space should be placed between licenses if there is more than one that
        applies. If an element in the license list is itself a list, it is
        interpreted as offering a choice of any one of the licenses in the
        sub-list.
        </para>

		<para>If the version number is a
		<quote>.0</quote> version, the <quote>.0</quote> should be
		omitted to make the version an integer. If the author gives the choice
		of using a given license or <quote>any later version</quote> of it,
		append a plus sign (+) to the version number. If the version
		specified in this case is also the earliest version,
		just leave out the version number entirely since it implies all
		versions.</para>

        <programlisting>license           GPL-3</programlisting>
        <programlisting>license           {freetype GPL}</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
</section>
