<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="reference.dependencies">
  <title>Dependencies</title>

  <para>Free and open source software is highly modular, and MacPorts ports
  often require that other ports be installed beforehand; these prerequisites
  for a given port are called a port's <quote>dependencies</quote>.</para>

  <para>The keywords used when specifying dependencies in a Portfile are
  related to port install phases, and they refer to what are called library,
  build, fetch, extract and run dependencies. Though all of them install dependencies
  before a given port is installed, specifying dependencies with the correct keyword
  is important for proper port upgrade and uninstall behavior, or when running targets
  other than install. For example,
  you may not uninstall a port that is a library dependency for another installed port,
  though you may remove one that is a build dependency. Likewise, if you run the
  fetch target for a port, only the fetch dependencies will be installed first, so
  they should be all that is needed for that target.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_fetch</term>

      <term>depends_fetch-append</term>

      <term>depends_fetch-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>fetch</option>, <option>checksum</option>,
        <option>extract</option>, <option>patch</option>,
        <option>configure</option>, <option>build</option>,
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Fetch dependencies are needed to download
        the distfiles for a port, and are not needed at all once the software
        is installed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_extract</term>

      <term>depends_extract-append</term>

      <term>depends_extract-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>extract</option>, <option>patch</option>,
        <option>configure</option>, <option>build</option>,
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Extract dependencies are needed to unpack a
        port's distfiles into the work directory, and are not needed at all once
        the software is installed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_build</term>

      <term>depends_build-append</term>

      <term>depends_build-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>configure</option>, <option>build</option>,
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Build dependencies are needed when software
        is being built, but not needed at all once it is installed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_lib</term>

      <term>depends_lib-append</term>

      <term>depends_lib-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>configure</option>, <option>build</option>,
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Library dependencies are needed both at
        build time (for headers and libraries to link against) and at run
        time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>depends_run</term>

      <term>depends_run-append</term>

      <term>depends_run-delete</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
        <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
        <option>package</option>. Run dependencies are needed when the
        software is run, but not to compile it.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <section id="reference.dependencies.types">
    <title>Port and File Dependencies</title>

    <para>There are two types of dependencies: port dependencies and file
    dependencies. Port dependencies can be satisfied by reference to a port
    (the MacPorts registry is queried), or by reference to a file (whether
    provided by a port or not). The most commonly-used type of dependencies in
    Portfiles are port dependencies, because dependencies should be provided
    by MacPorts ported software whenever possible, and usually only one port
    can provide the needed libraries and files.</para>

    <para>But when satisfying a dependency with vendor-supplied software is
    preferred for special reasons, or when it is possible for more than one
    port to satisfy a dependency, then file dependencies may be used. An
    example of the former is with ubiquitous utilities like awk, grep, make or
    sed, where OS X's versions are often sufficient; an example of the latter
    is with <quote>-devel</quote> ports—these ports provide a different
    version of the same files (though only one can be activated at a
    time).</para>

    <para>Port dependencies, the preferred type, are specified as shown in
    these examples:</para>

    <programlisting>depends_lib         port:rrdtool port:apache2

depends_build       port:libtool

depends_run         port:apache2 port:php5</programlisting>

    <para>File dependencies may be of three types: <option>bin</option> for
    programs, <option>lib</option> for libraries, and <option>path</option>
    for any installed file. File dependencies are specifed in the form:
    <replaceable>&lt;type&gt;</replaceable>:<replaceable>&lt;filespec&gt;</replaceable>:<replaceable>&lt;port&gt;</replaceable>.</para>
    
    <para>For <option>bin</option> dependencies,
    <replaceable>&lt;filespec&gt;</replaceable> is the name of a program in a
    bin directory like <filename>${prefix}/bin</filename>, /usr/bin, /bin, and
    the associated sbin directories.</para>
    
    <para>For <option>lib</option> dependencies,
    <replaceable>&lt;filespec&gt;</replaceable> is the name of a library
    (but without its extension) in a lib directory like
    <filename>${prefix}/lib</filename>, /usr/lib, /lib, some Framework
    directories, and those found in environment variables like DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH.</para>
    
    <para>For <option>path</option> dependencies,
    <replaceable>&lt;filespec&gt;</replaceable> is the complete absolute path
    to the file, or more usually, when the file is inside
    <filename>${prefix}</filename>, it is specified relative to
    <filename>${prefix}</filename>.
    Since <option>path</option> dependencies are the only ones which would find
    files only in an absolute path or a path inside <filename>${prefix}</filename>
    they are - in cases when a port needs to be more restrictive - often used
    instead of <option>bin</option> and <option>lib</option> dependencies .</para>

    <para>Note that the <replaceable>&lt;port&gt;</replaceable> specified is
    only installed if the specified library, binary, or file is not found. See
    the examples below:</para>

    <programlisting>depends_lib         lib:libX11.6:xorg

depends_build       bin:glibtool:libtool

depends_run         path:lib/libltdl.a:libtool</programlisting>
  </section>
</section>
