<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="reference.keywords">
  <title>Global Keywords</title>

  <para>MacPorts keywords are used to specify required or optional items
  within a Portfile, or to override default options used by MacPorts base for
  individual ports. Keywords are to be used within the "global" and "variant"
  sections of Portfiles, and not within optional port phase
  declarations.</para>

  <para>The global keywords listed below specify information for ports as a
  whole, whereas the keywords listed under a port phase specify information to
  be used during a particular installation phase.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>PortSystem</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The top line of every Portfile; it must be followed by a blank
        line. It defines which version of the Portfile interpreter will be
        used.</para>

        <programlisting>PortSystem          1.0

</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>name</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The name of the Port; it should be lowercase to prevent
        uninstallation problems due to a macports base bug.</para>

        <programlisting>name                foo</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>version</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The version of the ported software.</para>

        <programlisting>version             1.23.45</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>revision</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Optional keyword (default is 0) that is used to track port
        revisions. It should not be incremented for port revisions unless it
        would benefit users to upgrade an installed port, and cleared when the
        port is updated to a newer version.</para>

        <para>It should be used if a bug in the Portfile was found and all
        installations of this port have to be updated. If the change only
        affects new installations, there is no need to increase it.</para>

        <programlisting>revision            1</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>epoch</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An optional keyword (default value is 0) that may be used when
        ports are updated to a version that is numerically less than the
        previous version. For example 1.10 -&gt; 1.2 or 20070928 -&gt; 1.0. An
        epoch ensures that port version comparisons work correctly in these
        cases. Often the epoch is formatted like a date, but it can simply be
        a number such as 1.</para>

        <programlisting>epoch               20080924</programlisting>

        <programlisting>epoch               1</programlisting>

        <note>
          <para>An epoch is not needed for most ports. If an epoch is used it
          must never be decreased or removed even when a port's version is
          updated; this would cause port version comparisons to be incorrect
          since epochs take precedence over versions once epochs have been
          used.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>categories</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The category under which the ported software falls. The first
        category should be the same as the directory within which the Portfile
        is stored; secondary and tertiary categories may be selected.</para>

        <programlisting>categories          net security</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry id="reference.keywords.maintainers">
      <term>maintainers</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A port's maintainer is a person or persons who take
        responsibility for keeping the port up-to-date, and the maintainer
        keyword lists maintainer email addresses(s). However, many maintainers
        wish to hide these addresses from spambots; to do so follow these
        conventions:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>For addresses in domain @macports.org, simply omit the
            domain name.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For addresses in other domains, say
            <email>account@example.org</email>, use the convention
            example.org:account to specify the address.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In the example below, the maintainer email addresses
        <email>jdoe@macports.org</email> and
        <email>julesverne@example.org</email> are hidden using these
        conventions.</para>

        <programlisting>maintainers         jdoe \
                    example.org:julesverne</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>description</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A one-sentence description of the ported software.</para>

        <programlisting>description         A classic shooter arcade game.</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>long_description</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A long description of the ported software. Break long lines with
        escaped newlines.</para>

        <programlisting>long_description    A classic shooter arcade game derived from \
                    the game alien-munchers.  Not suitable for \
                    children under two years old.</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>homepage</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Port application's homepage.</para>

        <programlisting>homepage            http://www.example.org/apps</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>platforms</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The platforms on which the port has been tested.</para>

        <!-- TODO: add possible values -->

        <programlisting>platforms           darwin freebsd</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>