<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="reference.keywords">
  <title>Global Keywords</title>

  <para>MacPorts keywords are used to specify required or optional items
  within a Portfile, or to override default options used by MacPorts base for
  individual ports. Keywords are to be used within the "global" and "variant"
  sections of Portfiles, and not within optional port phase
  declarations.</para>

  <para>The global keywords listed below specify information for ports as a
  whole, whereas the keywords listed under a port phase specify information to
  be used during a particular installation phase.</para>

  <section id="reference.keywords.general">
    <title>General</title>

    <para>The list of global keywords.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>PortSystem</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The top line of every Portfile; it must be followed by a blank
          line. It defines which version of the Portfile interpreter will be
          used.</para>

          <programlisting>PortSystem          1.0

</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>name</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the Port; it should be lowercase to prevent
          uninstallation problems due to a macports base bug.</para>

          <programlisting>name                foo</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>version</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The version of the ported software.</para>

          <programlisting>version             1.23.45</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>revision</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Optional keyword (default is 0) that is used to track port
          revisions. It should not be incremented for port revisions unless it
          would benefit users to upgrade an installed port, and cleared when
          the port is updated to a newer version.</para>

          <para>It should be used if a bug in the Portfile was found and all
          installations of this port have to be updated. If the change only
          affects new installations, there is no need to increase it.</para>

          <programlisting>revision            1</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>epoch</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>An optional keyword (default value is 0) that may be used when
          a software developer updates an application to a version that is
          numerically less than the previous version. For example 1.10 -&gt;
          1.2 or 20070928 -&gt; 1.0. In these cases, an epoch may be used to
          ensure that port version comparisons are done properly. Often the
          epoch is formatted like a date, but it can simply be a number such
          as 1.</para>

          <programlisting>epoch               20080924</programlisting>

          <programlisting>epoch               1</programlisting>

          <note>
            <para>If an epoch is used it must be incremented for each
            subsequent port update; it must never be decreased or reset to
            zero, because this would always cause a port version comparison to
            be incorrect after a port upgrade.</para>
          </note>

          <para>An epoch is not be needed for most ports, and good use of a
          port's version can make using an epoch unneccesary even for
          application distributions without official version numbers. For
          example, if an application version 1.5 is superceded by a snapshot
          release 20081022, the new release could be given version number
          1.5.20081022, rather than 20081022, so the newer release will have a
          numericaly greater value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>categories</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The category under which the ported software falls. The first
          category should be the same as the directory within which the
          Portfile is stored; secondary and tertiary categories may be
          selected.</para>

          <programlisting>categories          net security</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>maintainers</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A port's maintainer is a person or persons who take
          responsibility for keeping the port up-to-date, and the maintainer
          keyword lists maintainer email addresses(s). However, many
          maintainers wish to hide these addresses from spambots; to do so
          follow these conventions:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>For addresses in domain @macports.org, simply omit the
              domain name.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For addresses in other domains, say
              <email>account@example.org</email>, use the convention
              example.org:account to specify the address.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>In the example below, the maintainer email addresses
          <email>jdoe@macports.org</email> and
          <email>julesverne@example.org</email> are hidden using these
          conventions.</para>

          <programlisting>maintainers         jdoe \
                    example.org:julesverne</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>description</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A one-sentence description of the ported software.</para>

          <programlisting>description         A classic shooter arcade game.</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>long_description</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A long description of the ported software. Break long lines
          with escaped newlines.</para>

          <programlisting>long_description    A classic shooter arcade game derived from \
                    the game alien-munchers.  Not suitable for \
                    children under two years old.</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>homepage</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Port application's homepage.</para>

          <programlisting>homepage            http://www.example.org/apps</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>platforms</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The platforms on which the port has been tested.</para>

          <programlisting>platforms           darwin freebsd</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="reference.keywords.dependencies">
    <title>Dependencies</title>

    <para>Free and open source software is highly modular, and MacPorts ports
    often require that other ports be installed beforehand; these
    prerequisites for a given port are called a port's
    <quote>dependencies</quote>.</para>

    <para>There are three types of MacPorts dependencies: library, build, and
    run dependencies. Dependency types are important for proper port upgrade
    and uninstall behavior. For example, you may not uninstall a port that is
    a library dependency for another port, though you may remove one with a
    build dependency; likewise, upgrading a port will upgrade its library and
    build dependencies also, but not its run dependencies.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>depends_lib</term>

        <term>depends_lib-append</term>

        <term>depends_lib-delete</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
          <option>configure</option>, <option>build</option>,
          <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
          <option>package</option>. Library dependencies are needed both at
          build time (for headers and libraries to link against) and at run
          time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>depends_build</term>

        <term>depends_build-append</term>

        <term>depends_build-delete</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
          <option>build</option>, <option>destroot</option>,
          <option>install</option>, and <option>package</option>. Build
          dependencies are needed when software is compiled, but not needed at
          all once the software is compiled and installed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>depends_run</term>

        <term>depends_run-append</term>

        <term>depends_run-delete</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The list of dependencies to check before phases
          <option>destroot</option>, <option>install</option>, and
          <option>package</option>. Run dependencies are needed when the
          software is run, but not to compile it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <section id="reference.keywords.dependencies.types">
      <title>Port and Non-Port Dependencies</title>

      <para>Port dependencies should be provided by MacPorts ports whenever
      possible, however dependencies may be provided by vendor-supplied
      software when satisfying a dependency by a port is not practical or
      desirable for a special reason. Dependencies of this type are called
      non-port dependencies.</para>

      <para>Non-port dependencies should only be used if the application or
      library can be installed by multiple ports (for example stable and
      -devel version) or if it can't be installed with Macports.</para>

      <para>Port dependencies, the preferred type, are specified as shown in
      these examples:</para>

      <programlisting>depends_lib         port:rrdtool port:apache2

depends_build       port:libtool

depends_run         port:apache2 port:php5</programlisting>

      <para>Non-port dependencies are specified as shown in these
      examples:</para>

      <programlisting>depends_lib         lib:libX11.6:xorg

depends_build       bin:glibtool:libtool

depends_run         path:${prefix}/lib/libltdl.a:libtool</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reference.keywords.variants">
    <title>Variants</title>

    <para>MacPorts variants are conditional modifications of port installation
    behavior that may be invoked by a user at the time of port install.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>variant [requires variant] [conflicts variant] [description
        description]</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The variant declaration may contain any keywords that can be
          placed in a Portfile's global section. If you wish to execute system
          (shell) calls or Tcl extensions during the execution of a port
          phase, you should place those statements within a
          <literal>variant_isset</literal> conditional within a phase
          declaration and not within the variant declaration itself.
          Dependencies and conflicts with other variants in the same port can
          be expressed with requires and conflicts. See the isset Tcl
          extension.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: no</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>variant gnome requires glib {
    configure.args-append   --with-gnome
    depends_lib-append      port:gnome-session
}</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>default_variants</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>If variants are defined, then the default_variants value lists
          which variants are enabled by default. This allows for Portfile
          modularity and also allows users to suppress default variants if
          they wish.</para>

          <para>Due to a bug in the current Macports base default_variants
          shouldn't be used at the moment as they cause problems while
          upgrading ports.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: none</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>default_variants    +ssl +tcpd

</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default variants may be suppressed by preceding a variant name
          with a "-" as shown in this example.</para>

          <programlisting><prompt>%%</prompt> <userinput>port install foo -ssl</userinput></programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>universal_variant</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>When using MacPorts on Mac OS X, a universal variant is
          defined by default to configure ports with universal flags. The
          variant can be overridden if the default code does not work (see the
          Configure Universal section below), or suppressed if a universal
          variant is not possible for the port with this keyword.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: yes</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>universal_variant   no</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="reference.keywords.livecheck">
    <title>Livecheck / Distcheck</title>

    <para>Options livecheck and distcheck are especially useful for port
    maintainers, but others may also find this information valuable.</para>

    <para>Livecheck checks to see if MacPorts can query the developer's
    download site to determine if a newer version of the software has become
    available since the port was installed.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.check</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Specify what kind of update check to perform.</para>

          <para>Open source mirror site options are to use the project's
          latest file release from <option>sourceforge</option> or
          <option>googlecode</option>, or the project's
          <literal>date_updated</literal> XML tag for
          <option>freshmeat</option>.</para>

          <para>Generic download site options are to specify a
          <option>moddate</option> (modification date) of a URL resource), a
          <option>regex</option> (retrieve the version by applying a regex to
          a URL resource), <option>regexm</option> (retrieve the version by
          applying a multi-line regex to a URL resource), <option>md5</option>
          (compares the md5 sum of a URL resource) or <option>none</option>
          (no check).</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: sourceforge or googlecode if the master_sites is
              one of these, else freshmeat.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: freshmeat sourceforge googlecode moddate regex
              regexm md5 none</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Examples:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.check     regex
livecheck.url       ${homepage}
livecheck.regex     "Generally Available (\\d+(?:\\.\\d+)*)"</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.name</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Name of the project for live checks; only used with freshmeat,
          sourceforge, and googlecode livechecks.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: <varname>${name}</varname> or the
              sourceforge/freshmeat/googlecode project name if it can be
              guessed from <literal>master_sites</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: <replaceable>any_project_name</replaceable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.name      hibernate</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.distname</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Name of the file release for sourceforge and googlecode
          checks. You may use this keyword without livecheck.version if you
          replace the version part of the name with "(.*)".</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: SourceForge: <varname>${livecheck.name}</varname>
              ; GoogleCode: first ${distfiles} item</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: <replaceable>filename</replaceable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.distname  faad2.src</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.version</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Version of the project for a check; used for regex-based
          checks.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: <varname>${version}</varname></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: <replaceable>any_version</replaceable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.version   ${name}-${version}</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.url</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>URL to query for a check.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>homepage or the first hit among the following
                  sites</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>http://freshmeat.net/projects-xml/${livecheck.name}/${livecheck.name}.xml</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>http://sourceforge.net/export/rss2_projfiles.php?project=${livecheck.name}</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>http://code.google.com/p/${livecheck.name}/downloads/list</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: <replaceable>any_url</replaceable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.url       http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/bison/</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.regex</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Regular expression to parse the resource for regex checks. Be
          sure to use a regular expression grouping around the version
          component.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: none</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: <replaceable>any_regex</replaceable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.regex     4th-([a-z0-9.]+)-unix.tar.gz</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>livecheck.md5</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>md5 checksum to use for an md5 comparison.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: none</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: <replaceable>any_md5_checksum</replaceable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>livecheck.md5       37e6a5b6516a680c7178b72021d3b706</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Distcheck reports whether or not the distfile(s) specified in a
    Portfile are still available on the developer's download site. Examples
    are given below.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>distcheck.check</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This option can be used to disable distcheck. It specifies
          what kind of check should be performed on distfiles: moddate (check
          if the Portfile is older than the distfile) or none (no
          check).</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Default: moddate</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Values: moddate none</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Example:</para>

              <programlisting>distcheck.check     none</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</section>