<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- -*- coding: utf-8; tab-width: 4; indent-tabs-mode: nil; c-basic-offset: 4 -*- vim:fenc=utf-8:et:sw=4:ts=4:sts=4:tw=120
-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY macports-prev-version "2.3.3">
<!ENTITY macports-version "2.3.4">
]>
<chapter id="using">
    <title>Using MacPorts</title>

    <para>This chapter describes using <command>port</command>, port variants, common tasks and port
    binaries.</para>

    <section id="using.port">
        <title>The port Command</title>

        <para><command>port</command> is the main utility used to interact with MacPorts. It is
            used to update <filename>Portfile</filename>s and the MacPorts infrastructure, and install and manage
            ports.</para>

        <section id="using.port.help">
            <title>port help</title>

            <para>The <option>help</option> action shows some brief information about the specified action, or if no
                action is specified, shows basic usage information for <command>port</command> in general.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>port help selfupdate</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
Usage: selfupdate --nosync

Upgrade MacPorts itself and run the sync target

--nosync   Do not run the sync target, i.e., do not update the ports tree.
           Only checks for (and installs, if available) new versions of
           MacPorts.</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.selfupdate">
            <title>port selfupdate</title>

            <para>The <option>selfupdate</option> action should be used regularly to update the local ports tree with
                the global MacPorts ports repository so you will have the latest versions of software packages
                available. It also checks for new releases of MacPorts itself, and upgrades it when necessary.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo port selfupdate</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
<!--        -->---&gt; Updating MacPorts base sources using rsync
<!--        -->MacPorts base version &macports-version; installed,
<!--        -->MacPorts base version &macports-version; downloaded.
<!--        -->---&gt; Updating the ports tree
<!--        -->---&gt; MacPorts base is already the latest version</screen>

            <para>If <option>selfupdate</option> detects that a newer version of MacPorts is available, it automatically
                updates the installed copy of MacPorts base to the latest released version. In that case, you will see
                this message:</para>

            <screen>
<!--        -->---&gt; Updating MacPorts base sources using rsync
<!--        -->MacPorts base version &macports-prev-version; installed,
<!--        -->MacPorts base version &macports-version; downloaded.
<!--        -->---&gt; Updating the ports tree
<!--        -->---&gt; MacPorts base is outdated, installing new version &macports-version;
<!--        -->Installing new MacPorts release in /opt/local as root:admin; permissions 755</screen>

            <para>If the <option>selfupdate</option> procedure fails you'll see a message like this:</para>

            <screen>Error installing new MacPorts base: command execution failed</screen>

            <para>As always, you can use the debug flag <option>-d</option> to enable verbose output. If your
                <option>selfupdate</option> failed, re-run it with debug output enabled to see all output generated by
                the build system.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo port -d selfupdate</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>The output may give you an idea why the build failed. Look for the first occurrences of
                <quote>error</quote>. If you cannot figure out what's wrong yourself, feel free to ask on the
                <email>macports-users@lists.macosforge.org</email> mailing list and attach the output generated by
                <command>sudo port -d selfupdate</command>.</para>

            <para><option>selfupdate</option> accepts a single switch:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--nosync</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Only update MacPorts itself, do not update the tree of <filename>Portfile</filename>s.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.sync">
            <title>port sync</title>

            <para>The <option>sync</option> action performs a subset of <option>selfupdate</option>. It synchronizes the
                ports tree, as does <option>selfupdate</option>, but it does not check for MacPorts upgrades. On OS X,
                unless there is a special reason not to do so, run <link
                    linkend="using.port.selfupdate">selfupdate</link> instead.</para>

            <para><option>sync</option> does not accept any switches.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.diagnose">
            <title>port diagnose</title>

            <para>The <option>diagnose</option> action checks for common issues in the user's environment and reports all
                issues it finds to the user, along with possible fixes for said problem.</para>

            <para><option>diagnose</option> accepts a single switch:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--quiet</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Only displays warnings and errors, rather than the status of all tests run.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

            <note>
                <para>This command will only be available in MacPorts version 2.4 and above.</para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.reclaim">
            <title>port reclaim</title>

            <para>The <option>reclaim</option> action attempts to reclaim space by uninstalling inactive ports, and
            removing unnecessary files that were downloaded during the installation process. </para>

            <para><option>reclaim</option> does not accept any switches.</para>

            <note>
                <para> This command will only be available in MacPorts version 2.4 and above.</para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.list">
            <title>port list</title>

            <para>The <option>list</option> action lists the currently available version of the specified ports, or if
                no ports are specified, displays a list of all available ports. The list of available ports is very
                long, so use <link linkend="using.port.search">search</link> if you are looking for a specific
                port.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>port list</userinput></programlisting>

            <note>
                <para><command>port list</command> always lists the most recent version available in MacPorts, which is
                    not necessarily the version you have installed. For this reason, <command>port list
                        installed</command> likely produces unexpected output. In most cases where you would
                    <option>list</option>, using <option>installed</option> or <option>echo</option> is the better
                    choice instead. Both <command>port installed</command> and <command>port echo installed</command>
                    would produce the output you might expect from the command, <command>port list installed</command>
                    will not (and, to make matters worse, will be slow).</para>

                <para>You will hardly need <command>port list</command> at all to work with MacPorts. When searching,
                    <command>port search</command> is the better choice and when trying to list ports, <command>port
                        installed</command> and <command>port echo</command> are much more useful.</para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.search">
            <title>port search</title>

            <para>The <option>search</option> action allows finding ports by partial matches of the name or description.
                Other fields can be matched against, and matched in different ways, by using options. <command>port
                    search</command> is the tool of choice if you are looking for a specific software in MacPorts. We
                recommend you read up on some of its flags to improve your efficiency when searching for ports. Run
                <command>port help search</command> for an exhaustive list of possible switches.</para>

            <para>Suppose you are looking for PHP in MacPorts. You might start with <command>port search php</command>
                and notice your query produces a lot of output. In fact, at the time of writing this, this search
                produces 661 matches. By default, <command>port search</command> searches both name and description of
                a port. While we're looking for PHP, we can reduce the number of hits by using the
                <option>--name</option> flag. Furthermore, we only want ports whose name starts with <quote>php</quote>,
                so we add the <option>--glob</option> flag (actually, we could leave it out because it is the default)
                and modify the search term to <userinput>php*</userinput>:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port search --name --glob 'php*'</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Furthermore, we can enable compact output by using the <option>--line</option> switch. This causes only
                a single line to be printed for each match:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port search --name --line --glob 'php*'</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Among a large number of PHP modules you will find the main PHP ports, which are named
                php<varname>&lt;version&gt;</varname>. Choose one to install.</para>

            <para>If you know regex and know about the format of the PHP versions, you can further reduce the output of
                <command>port search</command>:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port search --name --line --regex '^php\d*$'</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen><!--
            -->php     5.5       lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php4    4.4.9     lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php5    5.3.28    lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php52   5.2.17    lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php53   5.3.28    lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php54   5.4.31    lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php55   5.5.15    lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor
<!--        -->php56   5.6.0RC2  lang www    PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor</screen>

            <para>Let us look at another example that is less complicated. Assuming you are looking for
                <userinput>rrdtool</userinput>, a popular system to store and graph time-series data, the simple search
                approach works well:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port search rrd</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
cacti @0.8.8b (net)
    Cacti is a complete RRDtool network graphing solution.

jrrd @1.0.4 (java)
    Java interface to RRDTool

netmrg @0.20 (net)
    An RRDtool frontend for network monitoring, reporting, and graphing that generates day/week/month
    MRTG style graphs.

network-weathermap @0.97c (net)
    Weathermap is a network visualisation tool, to take graphs you already have and display an
    overview of your network as a map. It supports RRD, MRTG (RRD and old log-format), and
    tab-delimited text files. Other sources are via plugins or external scripts.

php-rrd @1.1.3 (php, net, devel)
    PHP rrdtool extension

php5-rrd @1.1.3 (php, net, devel)
    PHP rrdtool extension

php5-rrdtool @1.0.5 (php, net, devel)
    this port is only a stub and has been made obsolete by php5-rrd

php53-rrd @1.1.3 (php, net, devel)
    PHP rrdtool extension

php54-rrd @1.1.3 (php, net, devel)
    PHP rrdtool extension

php55-rrd @1.1.3 (php, net, devel)
    PHP rrdtool extension

rrdtool @1.4.7_5 (net)
    Round Robin Database

Found 11 ports.</screen>

            <para>The possible switches to <option>search</option> and their meaning are:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--case-sensitive</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Match the search string in a case-sensitive manner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--exact</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Match the literal search string exactly.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--glob</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Treat the given search string as glob search string (i.e., expand wildcards
                            <option>*</option>, <option>?</option>, and <option>[<varname>chars</varname>]</option>).
                            This is the default behavior.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--regex</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Treat the given search string as regular expression.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--<varname>&lt;field&gt;</varname></option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Test the search string against <varname>&lt;field&gt;</varname>. Can be specified multiple
                            times to test against multiple fields. The default is <option>--name --description</option>.
                            Possible values for <varname>&lt;field&gt;</varname> are</para>

                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--category</option>, <option>--categories</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Search for ports in a given category.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>
                                    <option>--depends</option>,
                                    <option>--depends_build</option>,
                                    <option>--depends_extract</option>,
                                    <option>--depends_fetch</option>,
                                    <option>--depends_lib</option>,
                                    <option>--depends_run</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Search for ports that depend on the port given as search string. The
                                        <option>--depends</option> is an alias for all other <option>--depends_</option>
                                        options combined. Note that only dependencies specified in default variants will
                                        be found.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--description</option>, <option>--long_description</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Test the search string against ports' descriptions.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--homepage</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Test the search string against the homepage field of all ports.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--maintainer</option>, <option>--maintainer</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Search for ports maintained by a specific maintainer.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--name</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Search only ports' names.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--portdir</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Test the search string against the path of the directory that contains the port.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>--variant</option>, <option>--variants</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Search for variant names.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.info">
            <title>port info</title>

            <para>The <option>info</option> action is used to get information about a port: name, version, description,
                variants, homepage, dependencies, license, and maintainers.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port info yubico-pam</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
yubico-pam @2.16 (security)
Variants:             universal

Description:          The Yubico PAM module provides an easy way to integrate the YubiKey into your
                      existing user authentication infrastructure. The module can be configured to
                      validate YubiKeys against Yubico's YubiCloud infrastructure, a custom YubiKey
                      validation server or it can be used for offline authentication with newer
                      YubiKeys supporting a challenge-response protocol.
Homepage:             https://github.com/Yubico/yubico-pam

Build Dependencies:   pkgconfig, autoconf, automake, libtool
Library Dependencies: ykpers, yubico-c-client
Platforms:            darwin
License:              BSD
Maintainers:          cal@macports.org</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.deps">
            <title>port deps</title>

            <para>The <option>deps</option> action lists the dependencies of a port. Dependencies are the packages are
                required by a port at runtime (library and runtime dependencies) or required to install it (build,
                fetch, and extract dependencies).</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port deps apache2</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>Full Name: apache2 @2.2.27_0+preforkmpm
<!--        -->Library Dependencies: apr, apr-util, expat, openssl, pcre, perl5, zlib</screen>

            <para>Note that the list of dependencies might depend on the variants you chose. For example, choosing the
                <option>+openldap</option> variant of <option>apache2</option> adds a dependency on
                <option>openldap</option>:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port deps apache2 +openldap</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>Full Name: apache2 @2.2.27_0+openldap+preforkmpm
<!--        -->Library Dependencies: apr, apr-util, expat, openssl, pcre, perl5, zlib, openldap</screen>

            <para><option>deps</option> accepts two switches:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--index</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do not read the <filename>Portfile</filename> to determine dependencies. Instead, rely on
                            the information cached in the port index. Note that (despite specifying them), this option
                            will ignore any effects of variants. It is, however, much faster.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--no-build</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Exclude dependencies only required at build time, i.e., fetch, extract, and build
                            dependencies.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

        </section>

        <section id="using.port.variants">
            <title>port variants</title>

            <para>The <option>variants</option> action allows you to check what variations of a port are available
                before you install it. Variants are a way for port authors to provide options you can use to customize
                your build at install time. See <link linkend="using.variants.invoking">Invoking Port Variants</link>
                below to install ports that have variants.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port variants apache2 +universal</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
apache2 has the variants:
   eventmpm: Use event MPM (experimental)
     * conflicts with preforkmpm workermpm
   openldap: Enable LDAP support through OpenLDAP
[+]preforkmpm: Use prefork MPM
     * conflicts with eventmpm workermpm
  +universal: Build for multiple architectures
   workermpm: Use worker MPM
     * conflicts with eventmpm preforkmpm</screen>

            <para>This output lists all variants followed by their description. If a variant depends on or conflicts
                with other variants, a line detailing that follows. A variant name prefixed by <option>+</option>
                indicates that it has been enabled (on the command line), while a prefix <option>-</option> indicates
                that it has been disabled. When bracketed, a prefix <option>+</option> means that the variant is enabled
                by default.
                Any <option>[]</option> are derived from the <filename>Portfile</filename>.
                While <option>()</option> are derived from the <filename>variants.conf</filename>.
                See <xref
                    linkend="internals.configuration-files.variants-conf" /> for more information on
                <filename>variants.conf</filename>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.install">
            <title>port install</title>

            <para>The action <option>install</option> is used to install a port. Once you determined the name of a port
                you want (possibly using <link linkend="using.port.search"><command>port search</command></link>), you
                can install it using this command. See <xref linkend="using.variants.invoking" /> on how to choose
                variants when installing a new port. For example,</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port install apache2 -preforkmpm +workermpm</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>installs the <option>apache2</option> port without the <option>preforkmpm</option>, but with the
                <option>workermpm</option> variant.</para>

            <para>If the installation of a port fails, you can enable verbose or debug output by giving the
                <option>-v</option> or <option>-d</option> flag to port:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port -v install apache2</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>All debug information is also kept in <filename>main.log</filename> for the port you
                installed. Its path will be printed automatically if the installation fails. You can manually get the
                path using <command>port logfile <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></command>. Note that logfiles will
                automatically be deleted on successful installation.</para>

            <para>If the installation of a port fails, you should always clean and try again, i.e., run</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port clean <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>and re-execute the command you ran before.</para>

            <para>You might also want to try enabling trace mode, which can prevent conflicts caused by files installed
                by other ports or in common system locations, such as <filename>/usr/local</filename>. To do that,
                re-run the installation with the <option>-t</option> flag, i.e.,</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port -t install <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>If the port still fails to install after you have followed these steps, please <link
                    linkend="project.tickets">file a ticket</link> and attach the <filename>main.log</filename> of
                a clean attempt.</para>

            <note>
                <para>The installation of a single port consists of multiple phases. These phases are fetch, extract,
                    patch, configure, build, destroot, archive, and finally install. You may break up a port's
                    installation into smaller steps for troubleshooting by using the name of one of these phases as
                    action rather than <option>install</option>. For example</para>

                <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port destroot apache2</userinput></programlisting>

                <para>will run the installation of <option>apache2</option> until the destroot phase. See <xref
                    linkend="reference.phases" /> for a complete list of phases and a detailed description.</para>
            </note>

            <para><option>install</option> takes the following switches:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--no-rev-upgrade</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By default, a binary sanity check called <option>rev-upgrade</option> is run automatically
                            after each successful installation. Pass this flag, if you want to avoid running this step,
                            for example if you want to run it explicitly later after a number of installations using
                            <command>sudo port rev-upgrade</command>, or if you know it will detect problems but want to
                            defer dealing with them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--unrequested</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By default, each port you install using the <option>install</option> explicitly (contrary to ports
                            installed as a dependency of a different port) is marked as <quote>requested</quote>.
                            If you want MacPorts to treat a port you installed manually as if it was automatically installed
                            as a dependency (e.g., if a dependency failed to build and you re-tried installing the dependency only),
                            pass this flag.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.clean">
            <title>port clean</title>

            <para>The action <option>clean</option> deletes intermediate files created by MacPorts while installing
                a port. A <command>port clean</command> is often necessary when builds fail and should be the first
                thing to try after a failed installation attempt.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port clean <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para><command>port clean</command> can also be used to remove corrupted downloads after a failed
                <option>fetch</option> phase, by specifying the <option>--dist</option> flag:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port clean --dist <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>deletes all files that have been downloaded for the given port.</para>

            <para><option>clean</option> accepts the following options:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--archive</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove temporary archives.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--dist</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove downloaded files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--logs</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove log files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--work</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remove the <filename>work</filename> directory, i.e., the directory used by MacPorts to
                            build a software. This removes all traces of an attempted build and is the default
                            operation.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--all</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All of the above combined.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.uninstall">
            <title>port uninstall</title>

            <para>The <option>uninstall</option> action will remove an installed port. It is one of the actions you will
                use fairly often in MacPorts.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>MacPorts will refuse to uninstall ports that are still needed by other ports. For example:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall libcomerr</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
---&gt;  Unable to uninstall libcomerr @1.42.9_0, the following ports depend on it:
---&gt;    kerberos5 @1.11.3_0
---&gt;    subversion @1.8.9_0
---&gt;    subversion-perlbindings-5.16 @1.8.9_0
Error: port uninstall failed: Please uninstall the ports that depend on libcomerr first.</screen>

            <para>You can recursively uninstall all ports that depend on the given port before uninstalling the port
                itself to work around this. To do that, use the <option>--follow-dependents</option> flag.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall --follow-dependents libcomerr</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>You can also override this safety check using the <option>-f</option> (force) flag. <emphasis>Since
                    this will obviously break the dependents you shouldn't do this unless you know what you are
                    doing.</emphasis></para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port -f uninstall libcomerr</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Uninstalling a port will not uninstall ports that have been automatically installed as dependencies of
                the uninstalled port and are otherwise unused. You can trigger this behavior by passing the
                <option>--follow-dependencies</option> flag. Ports that were manually installed (i.e., are marked as
                <quote>requested</quote>) or have other dependents will not be removed. You can manually uninstall the
                unneeded ports later using the <option>leaves</option> pseudo-port, e.g., using <command>sudo port
                    uninstall leaves</command>.</para>

            <para><option>uninstall</option> supports the following switches:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--follow-dependents</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recursively uninstall ports that depend on the specified port before uninstalling the port
                            itself. See also the textual description above.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--follow-dependencies</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Also uninstall ports that were automatically installed as dependencies of the removed port
                            and are no longer needed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--no-exec</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Avoid running any uninstall hooks, such as commands that update cache files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.contents">
            <title>port contents</title>

            <para>The <option>contents</option> action displays a list of all files that have been installed by a given
                port. You can only use <option>contents</option> for ports you installed.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port contents xorg-renderproto</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
Port xorg-renderproto contains:
  /opt/local/include/X11/extensions/render.h
  /opt/local/include/X11/extensions/renderproto.h
  /opt/local/lib/pkgconfig/renderproto.pc
  /opt/local/share/doc/renderproto/renderproto.txt</screen>

            <para>Common uses for <option>contents</option> are finding the location of a port's executable after
                installing it. The following line is usually helpful in this case:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port -q contents <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname> | grep -E '/s?bin/'</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>The <option>-q</option> (quiet) flag suppresses the header line in this case, but is not strictly necessary.</para>

            <para><option>contents</option> accepts:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--size</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Prints a human-readable representation of the files' sizes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--units UNIT</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Used in conjunction with <option>--size</option> to choose the unit of the file size.
                            Valid parameters for <option>UNIT</option> are</para>

                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>B</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>K</option>, <option>Ki</option>, or <option>KiB</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in <option>KiB</option>, i.e., 1024 bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>Mi</option>, or <option>MiB</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in <option>MiB</option>, i.e., 1024 * 1024 bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>Gi</option>, or <option>GiB</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in <option>GiB</option>, i.e., 1024 * 1024 * 1024 bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>

                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>k</option>, or <option>kB</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in <option>kB</option>, i.e., 1000 bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>M</option>, or <option>MB</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in <option>MB</option>, i.e., 1000 * 1000 bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>G</option>, or <option>GB</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>List sizes in <option>GB</option>, i.e., 1000 * 1000 * 1000 bytes.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.installed">
            <title>port installed</title>

            <para>The <option>installed</option> action displays the installed versions and variants of the specified
                ports, or if no ports are specified, all installed ports. It also displays whether a port is
                <quote>active</quote>, i.e., whether the files belonging to this port are currently present on disk or
                inactive, i.e., stashed away in a compressed tarball.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port installed</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
The following ports are currently installed:
  a52dec @0.7.4_0 (active)
  adns @1.4_0 (active)
  apache2 @2.2.27_0+preforkmpm (active)
  apr @1.5.1_0 (active)
  apr-util @1.5.3_0 (active)
  aquaterm @1.1.1_0 (active)
  asciidoc @8.6.9_1+python27 (active)
  …
  XviD @1.3.3_0 (active)
  xz @5.0.5_0 (active)
  yasm @1.2.0_0 (active)
  ykpers @1.12.0_0 (active)
  youtube-dl @2014.07.25.1_0+python27 (active)
  yubico-c-client @2.12_0 (active)
  yubico-pam @2.16_0 (active)
  zlib @1.2.8_0 (active)</screen>

            <para>Use <option>-v</option> to also display the platform and CPU architecture(s) for which the
                ports were built, and any variants which were explicitly negated.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port -v installed libsdl</userinput></programlisting>
            <screen>
The following ports are currently installed:
  libsdl @1.2.15_3-x11 (active) platform='darwin 13' archs='x86_64'</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.outdated">
            <title>port outdated</title>

            <para>The <option>outdated</option> action checks your installed ports against the current ports tree to see
                they have been updated since you installed them. Note that you will only get new versions by updating
                your ports tree using <option><link linkend="using.port.selfupdate">selfupdate</link></option> (or
                <option>sync</option>).</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port outdated</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
The following installed ports are outdated:
gnupg                          1.4.16_0 &lt; 1.4.18_0
gnupg2                         2.0.22_2 &lt; 2.0.25_0
gpg-agent                      2.0.22_1 &lt; 2.0.25_0
gpgme                          1.5.0_0 &lt; 1.5.1_0
HexFiend                       2.1.2_1 &lt; 2.3.0_0
libksba                        1.0.8_0 &lt; 1.3.0_0
p5.16-class-methodmaker        2.180.0_1 &lt; 2.210.0_0
p5.16-gnupg-interface          0.330.0_3 &lt; 0.500.0_1
p5.16-ipc-run                  0.910.0_1 &lt; 0.920.0_0</screen>

            <para><command>port outdated</command> lists the ports for which an upgrade is available and on the second
                column, why MacPorts thinks the port needs an upgrade. In most cases, this will be an increase in the
                version number. If it isn't, more details will be given.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.upgrade">
            <title>port upgrade</title>

            <para>The <option>upgrade</option> action upgrades installed ports and their dependencies to the latest
                version available in MacPorts. In most cases, you will run</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port upgrade outdated</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>to update all ports that have an upgrade available. You can, however, selectively upgrade ports if you
                want to delay other upgrades until later. This is not recommended unless you know what you are doing,
                since you might experience software errors for the ports that have not yet been upgraded. To upgrade
                individual ports, specify the name(s) of the port(s) to upgrade:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port upgrade gnupg2</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Note that MacPorts may decide to upgrade other dependent ports before upgrading the port you requested
                to be updated. Do not attempt to prevent this, since it will very likely lead to problems later.</para>

            <note>
                <para><option>upgrade</option> does not uninstall the old version of a port. Instead, it deactivates it,
                    i.e., it stashes the files belonging to the older version away in a tarball. This allows you to go
                    back to the older version if there happens to be a problem with the updated one. To do that,
                    run</para>

                <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port installed <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

                <para>to determine the version number of the old version you want to re-activate, and run</para>

                <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port activate <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname> @<varname>&lt;old-version&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

                <para>to go back to the old version.</para>

                <para>If you do not want to keep the old versions around while upgrading, you can pass
                    <option>-u</option> when upgrading:</para>

                <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port -u upgrade outdated</userinput></programlisting>

                <para>However, we instead recommend keeping the older versions around for a while and running</para>

                <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall inactive</userinput></programlisting>

                <para>once in a while.</para>
            </note>

            <para><option>upgrade</option> accepts a number of switches:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--force</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Always consider the given ports outdated, regardless of whether they actually are.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--enforce-variants</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the installed variants do not match those requested, upgrade (and change variants) even
                            if the port is not outdated. You can use this to switch the variant selection on an
                            installed port, e.g., using</para>

                        <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port upgrade --enforce-variants apache2 -preforkmpm +workermpm</userinput></programlisting>

                        <para>Note that <option>--enforce-variants</option> will also enforce your variant selection in
                            all dependencies. If you know this is not necessary, you can avoid processing dependencies
                            using the global <option>-n</option> flag:</para>

                        <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port -n upgrade --enforce-variants apache2 -preforkmpm +workermpm</userinput></programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--no-replace</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do not automatically install replacement ports for a port that you have installed, but was
                            replaced with a different one.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.dependents">
            <title>port dependents</title>

            <para>The <option>dependents</option> action reports what ports depend upon a given (installed) port, if
                any.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port dependents openssl</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>apache2 depends on openssl
curl depends on openssl
cyrus-sasl2 depends on openssl
git depends on openssl
kerberos5 depends on openssl
lftp depends on openssl
libssh depends on openssl
mosh depends on openssl
openldap depends on openssl
p5.16-net-ssleay depends on openssl
python27 depends on openssl
python32 depends on openssl
qt4-mac depends on openssl
ruby19 depends on openssl
serf1 depends on openssl
textmate2 depends on openssl
wireshark depends on openssl</screen>

            <para>Note that <option>dependents</option> does not work for ports that are not installed on your system.
                If you want to find out, which ports depend on a port that you have not installed, you can use</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port echo depends:<varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>This command will, however, not cover dependencies that are only present in non-default variants.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.livecheck">
            <title>port livecheck</title>

            <para>The <option>livecheck</option> action checks to see if the application corresponding to a given port
                has been updated at the developer's download site. This action is mostly useful for port maintainers to
                determine whether their port needs to be updated, but other may also wish to see if a port packages the
                latest available version. See <xref linkend="reference.livecheck" /> for more information on
                livecheck.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port livecheck rb19-sass</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>rb19-sass seems to have been updated (port version: 3.3.10, new version: 3.3.14)</screen>

            <note>
                <para>If <option>livecheck</option> finds no higher version at the port's download site, it prints
                    nothing. The option <option>-d</option> (debug) may be used for detailed livecheck processing
                    information.</para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section id="using.port.lint">
            <title>port lint</title>

            <para>The lint action checks if the <filename>Portfile</filename> conforms to the MacPorts standards
                    specified in <link linkend="development">Portfile Development</link>. You should use this if you
                    modified a <filename>Portfile</filename> before submitting patches back to MacPorts.</para>

            <para>If a <filename>Portfile</filename> validates fine the following message is shown.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port lint rb19-sass</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
---&gt;  Verifying Portfile for rb19-sass
---&gt;  0 errors and 0 warnings found.</screen>

            <para>Otherwise the warnings and errors are listed.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port lint abiword</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
---&gt;  Verifying Portfile for abiword
Warning: Variant use_binary does not have a description
Warning: Variant use_source does not have a description
Warning: no license set
---&gt;  0 errors and 3 warnings found.</screen>

            <para><option>lint</option> has the following flag:</para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--nitpick</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enables additional checks that are mostly whitespace-related and best practices.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="using.variants">
        <title>Port Variants</title>

        <para>Variants are a way for port authors to provide options for a port that may be chosen at installation.
            Typically, variants are optional features that can be enabled, but are not necessarily useful for all users
            and are thus not enabled by default. To display the available variants for a port, if any, use this
            command:</para>

        <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port variants <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

        <para>For example:</para>

        <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port variants apache2</userinput></programlisting>

        <screen>
apache2 has the variants:
   eventmpm: Use event MPM (experimental)
     * conflicts with preforkmpm workermpm
   openldap: Enable LDAP support through OpenLDAP
[+]preforkmpm: Use prefork MPM
     * conflicts with eventmpm workermpm
   universal: Build for multiple architectures
   workermpm: Use worker MPM
     * conflicts with eventmpm preforkmpm</screen>

         <para>This output lists all variants followed by their description. If a variant depends on or conflicts
                with other variants, a line with the details on that follows. Variant lines that have a
                <option>+</option> are enabled and those with <option>-</option> are disabled.
                Any <option>[]</option> are derived from the <filename>Portfile</filename>.
                While <option>()</option> are derived from the <filename>variants.conf</filename>.
                See <xref
                    linkend="internals.configuration-files.variants-conf" /> for more information on
            <filename>variants.conf</filename>.</para>

        <section id="using.variants.invoking">
            <title>Invoking Variants</title>

            <para>A variant can only be selected when a port is installed. After you have determined what variants
                a given port has, if any, you may install a port using the variant by specifying its name preceded by
                a plus or minus sign on the command line, for example</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port install apache2 +openldap</userinput></programlisting>
            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port install apache2 -preforkmpm +workermpm</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Note that you will not see any confirmation of successful variant selection and MacPorts will not warn
                you if you misspelled a variant's name. If your installation is successful, but the chosen feature still
                seems to be missing, check for possible typos. You can use <command><link
                        linkend="using.port.installed">port installed</link></command> to verify that the port has been
                installed with the chosen variant.</para>

            <para>This happens because MacPorts will also use the specified variants for any dependencies. For example,</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port install apache2 +mariadb</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>even though <option>apache2</option> does not have a <option>+mariadb</option> variant. Instead, this
                will cause the <option>apr-util</option> port to be installed with the <option>+mariadb</option>
                variant.</para>

            <para>MacPorts will remember the variants that were used when installing a port. If you upgrade a port
                later, the same variants will be used, unless you manually specify different variants.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.variants.negating">
            <title>Negating Default Variants</title>

            <para>A <filename>Portfile</filename> can specify a default set of variants that will be used when you do
                not manually override it. Not all ports specify default variants – if there are no default variants, no
                variants are chosen by default.</para>

            <para>If you wish to disable a variant that has been enabled by default, either by the
                <filename>Portfile</filename>, or by your configuration in <filename>variants.conf</filename>, you can
                negate the variant in question by prefixing the variant name with a minus on the command line:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port install apache2 -preformmpm +workermpm</userinput></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="using.common-tasks">
        <title>Common Tasks</title>

        <para>This section lists common operations you may want to perform when managing a MacPorts installation. These
            are the workflows you will need most while using MacPorts. We recommend you read at least this section as
            a primer into how to use MacPorts. More details about the usage can be found in <xref linkend="using.port"/>
            and the <option>port(1)</option> manpage available by running <command>man 1 port</command> in
            a Terminal.</para>

        <para>Mind the <quote>sudo</quote> for some of the subsequent examples, which is necessary if you have a default
            MacPorts installation.</para>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.updating">
            <title>Updating Your Ports Tree</title>

            <para>The local ports tree is a collection of files that contain information on which packages are available
                through MacPorts and how they can be installed. You should regularly update your ports tree to get
                access to updated versions of software and bug fixes. To do that, use <option>selfupdate</option>:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port selfupdate</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>Password:
<!--        -->---&gt; Updating MacPorts base sources using rsync
<!--        -->MacPorts base version &macports-version; installed,
<!--        -->MacPorts base version &macports-version; downloaded.
<!--        -->---&gt; Updating the ports tree
<!--        -->---&gt; MacPorts base is already the latest version
<!--        -->
<!--        -->The ports tree has been updated. To upgrade your installed ports, you should run
<!--        -->  port upgrade outdated</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.showports">
            <title>Show Ports Which Need Updating</title>

            <para>To see what's new after running <option>selfupdate</option>, you can use <command>port
                    outdated</command> to generate a list of ports that have newer versions available. This can help in
                estimating the time required for <command>sudo port upgrade outdated</command>, even though this depends
                on further factors such as binary package availability and a port's build time.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port outdated</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
<!--        -->The following installed ports are outdated:
<!--        -->gnupg                          1.4.16_0 &lt; 1.4.18_0
<!--        -->gnupg2                         2.0.22_2 &lt; 2.0.25_0
<!--        -->gpg-agent                      2.0.22_1 &lt; 2.0.25_0
<!--        -->gpgme                          1.5.0_0 &lt; 1.5.1_0
<!--        -->HexFiend                       2.1.2_1 &lt; 2.3.0_0
<!--        -->libksba                        1.0.8_0 &lt; 1.3.0_0
<!--        -->p5.16-class-methodmaker        2.180.0_1 &lt; 2.210.0_0
<!--        -->p5.16-gnupg-interface          0.330.0_3 &lt; 0.500.0_1
<!--        -->p5.16-ipc-run                  0.910.0_1 &lt; 0.920.0_0</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.upgrading">
            <title>Upgrading Outdated Ports</title>

            <para>To upgrade all your installed and outdated ports, run</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port upgrade outdated</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>In case you want to upgrade only a specific port (not recommended unless you know what you are doing),
                replace <quote>outdated</quote> in the command given above with the port's name:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port upgrade makedepend</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>Password:
<!--        -->---&gt; Computing dependencies for makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Fetching makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Attempting to fetch makedepend-1.0.3.tar.bz2 from http://lil.fr.distfiles.macports.org/makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Verifying checksum(s) for makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Extracting makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Configuring makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Building makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Staging makedepend into destroot
<!--        -->---&gt; Computing dependencies for makedepend
<!--        -->---&gt; Installing makedepend @1.0.3_0
<!--        -->---&gt; Deactivating makedepend @1.0.2_0
<!--        -->---&gt; Activating makedepend @1.0.3_0
<!--        -->---&gt; Cleaning makedepend</screen>

            <para>Note that MacPorts will upgrade any dependencies of a port first before updating the port itself. So
                even if you request the update of a single port only, other ports may be upgraded first because they are
                in the dependency tree. Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> try to avoid this, as it will very likely lead to
                problems later on – the new version of the port you want to upgrade might require the newer dependency,
                or it might only have been upgraded at all to be rebuilt against the updated dependency, in which case
                avoiding the update of the dependency defeats the purpose of the reinstallation.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.removeinactive">
            <title>Removing Inactive Version(s) of Upgraded Port(s)</title>

            <para>By default, upgrading ports in MacPorts does not remove the older versions. This is a safety measure
                to ensure you can go back to a working and tested version in case an update goes wrong. To save disk
                space, you should periodically uninstall any old versions you no longer need.</para>

            <para>Use</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port installed inactive</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>to get a list of inactive ports you likely no longer need.</para>

            <screen>The following ports are currently installed:
<!--        -->  gnupg @1.4.16_0
<!--        -->  gnupg2 @2.0.22_2
<!--        -->  gpg-agent @2.0.22_1
<!--        -->  gpgme @1.5.0_0
<!--        -->  HexFiend @2.1.2_1
<!--        -->  libksba @1.0.8_0
<!--        -->  p5.16-class-methodmaker @2.180.0_1
<!--        -->  p5.16-gnupg-interface @0.330.0_3
<!--        -->  p5.16-ipc-run @0.910.0_1</screen>

            <para>Check the list for any ports you might still want to keep. To remove all of them at once, run</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall inactive</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>Password:
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling p5.16-gnupg-interface @0.330.0_3
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning p5.16-gnupg-interface
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling gnupg @1.4.16_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gnupg
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling gpgme @1.5.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gpgme
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling gnupg2 @2.0.22_2
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gnupg2
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling gpg-agent @2.0.22_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gpg-agent
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling HexFiend @2.1.2_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning HexFiend
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling libksba @1.0.8_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning libksba
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling p5.16-class-methodmaker @2.180.0_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning p5.16-class-methodmaker
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling p5.16-ipc-run @0.910.0_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning p5.16-ipc-run</screen>

            <para>Of course you could also select only a specific inactive port, but that requires to specify the exact
                version:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall HexFiend @2.1.2_1</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>Password:
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling HexFiend @2.1.2_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning HexFiend</screen>

            <para>To uninstall all inactive ports but a single one, you can use the following shortcut:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall inactive and not <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.finddepending">
            <title>Finding Ports Depending on a Certain Port</title>

            <para>If you want to find all ports that depend on a given other port, you can use</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port echo depends:<varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>If you are only interested in the dependent ports that you actually have installed, you can use the
                quicker and more accurate <option>dependents</option>:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port dependents <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port dependents libksba</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>gnupg2 depends on libksba
<!--        -->gpg-agent depends on libksba</screen>

            <para>MacPorts also has a recursive version of the <option>dependents</option> action called <option>rdependents</option>:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port rdependents libksba</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>The following ports are dependent on libksba:
<!--        -->  gnupg2
<!--        -->    gpgme
<!--        -->  gpg-agent</screen>

            <para>Finally, to find out which port you manually installed caused the automatic installation of
                a dependency, use the following expression:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port installed requested and rdependentof:<varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port installed requested and rdependentof:libksba</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>The following ports are currently installed:
<!--        -->  gnupg2 @2.0.25_0 (active)</screen>
        </section>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.findleaves">
            <title>Finding Leaves</title>

            <para>After a while of using MacPorts, installing and uninstalling ports, packages that have been
                automatically installed as dependencies for other ports are left behind, even though they are no longer
                necessary. Ports that have not been manually installed (<quote>requested</quote>) and do not have any
                dependents are called <quote>leaves</quote> and can be identified using the <option>leaves</option>
                pseudo-port, for example in conjunction with the <option>echo</option> or <option>installed</option>
                action.</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port echo leaves</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
<!--        -->git-flow                       @0.4.1_2
<!--        -->gmake                          @4.0_0
<!--        -->gpgme                          @1.5.1_0
<!--        -->hs-download-curl               @0.1.4_0
<!--        -->pkgconfig                      @0.28_0
<!--        -->py27-docutils                  @0.12_0
<!--        -->python32                       @3.2.5_0
<!--        -->texi2html                      @5.0_1
<!--        -->yasm                           @1.2.0_0</screen>

            <para>These leaves may be wanted, but are in most cases unneeded. See <xref
                    linkend="using.common-tasks.keeplean"/> to find out how to mark some of the leaves as requested. You
                can uninstall all leaves using</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall leaves</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Note that the uninstallation can mark new ports as leaves. To uninstall all leaves, you have to repeat
                the process until <command>port echo leaves</command> comes back empty. To simplify this, consider
                installing the <option>port_cutleaves</option> port and running <command>sudo
                    port_cutleaves</command>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.common-tasks.keeplean">
            <title>Keep Your Installation Lean by Defining Leaves as Requested Ports</title>

            <para>Well, before we come to the procedure of defining your requested ports, let's have a look at a typical
                scenario where you want to understand what is actually installed and what is on the other hand truly
                necessary for your system. Say checking leaves of your MacPorts installation gives this output:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port echo leaves</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
<!--        -->git-flow                       @0.4.1_2
<!--        -->gmake                          @4.0_0
<!--        -->gpgme                          @1.5.1_0
<!--        -->hs-download-curl               @0.1.4_0
<!--        -->pkgconfig                      @0.28_0
<!--        -->py27-docutils                  @0.12_0
<!--        -->python32                       @3.2.5_0
<!--        -->texi2html                      @5.0_1
<!--        -->yasm                           @1.2.0_0</screen>

            <para>Now it is up to the user to decide what's needed and what is not. We've noticed
                <option>pkgconfig</option> is needed to build many ports, and while it is strictly not needed after
                installation, we'd like to keep it around to avoid installing it over and over again.
                <option>python32</option>, <option>texi2html</option>, and <option>yasm</option> are only needed to
                update <option>mplayer2</option>, and since that software is rarely updated, we will re-install those
                ports again when they are needed. Since they are all distributable, MacPorts will use pre-built binaries
                for their installation anyway, so re-installing them wouldn't take long anyway. We don't really know why
                the rest of the leaves were installed, so we're just going to remove them for now.</para>

            <para>Since we decided to keep <option>pkgconfig</option>, we are going to mark it as manually installed
                (<quote>requested</quote> in MacPorts lingo) using:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port setrequested pkgconfig</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>When you've step-by-step figured out which ports you want to keep on your system and have set them as
                requested, you'll have a list of unnecessary ports, which you can get rid of using</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port uninstall leaves</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Note that uninstalling leaves may mark new ports as leaves, so you will have to repeat the process.
                You can install the <option>port_cutleaves</option> port, which is a special script for the job. It
                allows you to interactively decide whether to keep or uninstall a port. Run it as</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port_cutleaves</userinput></programlisting>

            <screen>
<!--        -->[Leaf 1 of 8] hs-download-curl @0.1.4_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort:
<!--        -->** hs-download-curl @0.1.4_0 will be kept.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 2 of 8] gmake @4.0_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** gmake @4.0_0 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 3 of 8] texi2html @5.0_1 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** texi2html @5.0_1 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 4 of 8] yasm @1.2.0_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** yasm @1.2.0_0 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 5 of 8] python32 @3.2.5_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** python32 @3.2.5_0 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 6 of 8] py27-docutils @0.12_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** py27-docutils @0.12_0 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 7 of 8] git-flow @0.4.1_2 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** git-flow @0.4.1_2 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 8 of 8] gpgme @1.5.1_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** gpgme @1.5.1_0 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating gmake @4.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gmake
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling gmake @4.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gmake
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating texi2html @5.0_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning texi2html
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling texi2html @5.0_1
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning texi2html
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating yasm @1.2.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning yasm
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling yasm @1.2.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning yasm
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating python32 @3.2.5_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning python32
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling python32 @3.2.5_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning python32
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating py27-docutils @0.12_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning py27-docutils
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling py27-docutils @0.12_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning py27-docutils
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating git-flow @0.4.1_2
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning git-flow
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling git-flow @0.4.1_2
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning git-flow
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating gpgme @1.5.1_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gpgme
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling gpgme @1.5.1_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning gpgme
<!--        -->
<!--        -->The following ports were uninstalled:
<!--        -->  gmake @4.0_0
<!--        -->  texi2html @5.0_1
<!--        -->  yasm @1.2.0_0
<!--        -->  python32 @3.2.5_0
<!--        -->  py27-docutils @0.12_0
<!--        -->  git-flow @0.4.1_2
<!--        -->  gpgme @1.5.1_0
<!--        -->
<!--        -->Search for new leaves?
<!--        -->  [no] / (y)es: y
<!--        -->
<!--        -->[Leaf 1 of 1] py27-roman @2.0.0_0 (active):
<!--        -->  [keep] / (u)ninstall / (f)lush / (a)bort: u
<!--        -->** py27-roman @2.0.0_0 will be uninstalled.
<!--        -->
<!--        -->---&gt;  Deactivating py27-roman @2.0.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning py27-roman
<!--        -->---&gt;  Uninstalling py27-roman @2.0.0_0
<!--        -->---&gt;  Cleaning py27-roman
<!--        -->
<!--        -->The following ports were uninstalled:
<!--        -->  py27-roman @2.0.0_0
<!--        -->
<!--        -->Search for new leaves?
<!--        -->  [no] / (y)es: y
<!--        -->
<!--        -->There are no new leaves to process.</screen>

            <para>You can get a list of all ports you previously set as requested (or installed manually) using:</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port installed requested</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>We recommend you check the list of leaves from time to time to keep your system free of too much
                <quote>garbage</quote>. You should also periodically check the list of your requested ports and mark any
                ports you no longer need as unrequested using</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port unsetrequested <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Then check for new leaves to cut down the number of installed ports and the size of your MacPorts
                installation.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="using.binaries">
        <title>Port Binaries</title>

        <para>MacPorts can pre-compile ports into binaries so applications need not be compiled when installing on
            a target system. MacPorts supports two types of binaries: archives and packages.</para>

        <section id="using.binaries.archives">
            <title>Binary Archives</title>

            <para>Binary archives can only be used on a target system running MacPorts. They allow MacPorts utilities to
                skip the build (which is usually the phase that takes longest) and begin installation after the destroot
                phase. Binary archives are automatically created whenever a port is installed, and can also be
                downloaded from a server. MacPorts runs a buildbot infrastructure that creates prebuilt binary packages
                for all ports in MacPorts for the default installation prefix. Buildbots exist for systems later or
                equal to Snow Leopard. If a port builds successfully and its license and those of its dependencies allow
                binary redistribution, they archives are uploaded to <option>packages.macports.org</option> and will be
                automatically used by MacPorts during installation.</para>

            <para>You can manually create an archive (and see debug output for its creation) using</para>

            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port -d archive logrotate</userinput></programlisting>
            <screen>
<!--        -->---&gt;  Installing logrotate @3.8.6_2+gzip
<!--        -->[…]
<!--        -->DEBUG: Creating logrotate-3.8.6_2+gzip.darwin_13.x86_64.tbz2
<!--        -->[…]
<!--        -->a .
<!--        -->a ./+COMMENT
<!--        -->a ./+CONTENTS
<!--        -->a ./+DESC
<!--        -->a ./+PORTFILE
<!--        -->a ./+STATE
<!--        -->a ./opt
<!--        -->a ./opt/local
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/etc
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/sbin
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/var
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/var/run
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/var/run/logrotate
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/var/run/logrotate/.turd_logrotate
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/logrotate
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/man
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/man/man5
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/man/man8
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/man/man8/logrotate.8.gz
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/man/man5/logrotate.conf.5.gz
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/logrotate/CHANGES
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/logrotate/COPYING
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/logrotate/logrotate.conf.example
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/share/logrotate/org.macports.logrotate.plist.example
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/sbin/logrotate
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/etc/logrotate.d
<!--        -->a ./opt/local/etc/logrotate.d/.turd_logrotate
<!--        -->DEBUG: Archive logrotate-3.8.6_2+gzip.darwin_13.x86_64.tbz2 packaged</screen>

            <para>Binary archive files are placed in <filename>${prefix}/var/macports/software/</filename>. The archive
                file type is set in <filename>macports.conf</filename> using the
                <option>portarchivetype</option> key. The default format is <option>tbz2</option>; other options are:
                <option>tar</option>, <option>tbz</option>, <option>tbz2</option>, <option>tgz</option>,
                <option>tlz</option>, <option>txz</option>, <option>xar</option>, <option>zip</option>,
                <option>cpgz</option>, and <option>cpio</option>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="using.binaries.binary-packages">
            <title>Binary Packages</title>

            <para>Binary packages are standalone binary installers that are precompiled; they do not require MacPorts on
                the target system. As such, they are helpful in generating disk images or installers to be redistributed
                to users without relying on MacPorts for installation. Binary installers created with MacPorts are
                usually <option>.pkg</option> (OS X Installer Packages). MacPorts can also convert
                a <option>.pkg</option> package into an OS X <option>.dmg</option> disk image. You can create binary
                packages using <command>port</command> as shown in the following examples.</para>

            <warning>
                <para>If you want to create installer packages using MacPorts for redistribution, make sure you do not
                    use a standard installation of MacPorts in <filename>/opt/local</filename>. If you do that, your
                    installer package conflicts with MacPorts on systems that <emphasis>do</emphasis> have MacPorts
                    installed.</para>

                <para>Instead, follow <xref linkend="installing.macports.source.multiple"/> and choose a prefix specific
                    to the software you are trying to package, e.g., <filename>/opt/logrotate</filename> for
                    <option>logrotate</option>. Then use this custom MacPorts installation to build your package.</para>
            </warning>

            <para>Create an OS X <option>.pkg</option> installer for the <option>pstree</option> port:</para>
            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port pkg pstree</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>You may also create an OS X <option>.dmg</option> disk image file instead:</para>
            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port dmg pstree</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>In most cases you probably want to package a port and all its library and runtime dependencies in
                a single package. You can use a metapackage to do this. Create one using:</para>
            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port mpkg gimp2</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>Just as with a single package, a metapackage can also be wrapped in a <option>.dmg</option>.</para>
            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>sudo port mdmg gimp2</userinput></programlisting>

            <para>All packages are placed in a port's work directory, which you can locate using:</para>
            <programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>port work <varname>&lt;portname&gt;</varname></userinput></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
