<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="portimages">
  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>
				images
      </keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  
  <title>MacPorts Port Images</title> 
  
  <sect1>
    <title>About this chapter</title>

		<para>This chapter provides an overview of the MacPorts Port
			Image model of installing and using ports for users of
			MacPorts.  A more complete overview of Port Images can be found
			in the MacPorts Internals part of this Guide.</para>
  </sect1>
	
  <sect1 id='what'>
    <title>What Are Port Images?</title>
   
		<para>Port Images are a new model for installing and using your
			ported software.  At the most basic level, Port Images are a
			solution to the problem of needing or wanting multiple different
			versions, revisions, and/or variants of the same port installed at
			the same time.  This is accomplished by installing the port into a
			repository location and then create links, or aliases, from that
			repository location into the <varname>${prefix}</varname> from
			where you can use the MacPorts ports.</para>

		<para>Port Images provide the ability to test new versions of a
			port, or different variants of a port, without having to uninstall
			a previous and/or working version of that port.  This is
			accomplished using one of the key concepts of Images:
			<emphasis>activation</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>
	<sect1 id="activation">
		<title>Port Image Activation</title>

		<para>With Port Images in MacPorts, the port is installed as an
			<emphasis>image</emphasis> to the MacPorts <emphasis>image
			repository</emphasis>.  This repository can be thought of as an
			library of ports that actually contains all of the files belonging
			to that port.  Once the port is installed as an image, the port
			can be <emphasis>activated</emphasis>.</para>
			
		<para>Activation simply creates the links into the
			<varname>${prefix}</varname> of MacPorts.  MacPorts manages
			any conflicts between any ports that are activated, and will
			inform you if one port is attempting to link a file that already
			exists and belongs to another port.  You have the option to force
			MacPorts to go ahead and activate the port in the event of a
			conflict, and MacPorts will continue, moving the old file out
			of the way.</para>

		<para>By default, MacPorts will go ahead and activate a port when
			you run <userinput>port install vim</userinput>.  Once a port is
			installed and activated, you can <emphasis>deactivate</emphasis>,
			in addition to <emphasis>uninstalling</emphasis> it.  If you wish
			to move one port out of the way of another port or another variant
			or version of the same port, you can <emphasis>deactivate
			it</emphasis>.  When you do this, the port is still installed in
			the <emphasis>image repository</emphasis>, but simply not linked
			into <varname>${prefix}</varname>.</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="using_images">
		<title>Using Port Images</title>

		<para>MacPorts uses Port Images by default now, so if you are
			using a recent release of MacPorts, you are using Port Images!
			Port Images will work transparently for users used to the old
			installation model of MacPorts, as well as those familiar with
			other port systems.  If you wish to use the advanced features that
			Port Images provide, namely activation and deactivation, the
			following commands are available:</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><userinput>port installed vim</userinput></term>
					
				<listitem>
					<para>This command will list all installed versions and
					variants of the <varname>vim</varname> port.  You can use this
					command to find the version string the port if you have
					multiple versions installed and wish to activate or deactivate
					one version.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><userinput>port activate vim</userinput></term>
					
				<listitem>
					<para>This command will activate the <varname>vim</varname>
					port.  If there are multiple versions of the
					<varname>vim</varname> port installed, you will need to
					provide the version string of the port you wish to
					activate.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><userinput>port activate vim @6.2.532+gtk2</userinput></term>
					
				<listitem>
					<para>This command will activate the specific version of the
					<varname>vim</varname> given using the version string.  This
					is how you activate one version of a port out of two or more
					installed versions of that port.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><userinput>port deactivate vim</userinput></term>
					
				<listitem>
					<para>This command will deactivate the <varname>vim</varname>
					port.  If there are multiple versions of the
					<varname>vim</varname> port installed, you will need to
					provide the version string of the port you wish to
					deactivate.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><userinput>port deactivate vim @6.2.532+gtk2</userinput></term>
					
				<listitem>
					<para>This command will deactivate the specific version of the
					<varname>vim</varname> given using the version string.  This
					is how you deactivate one version of a port out of two or more
					installed versions of that port.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><userinput>port location vim</userinput></term>
					
				<listitem>
					<para>This command will simply give you the full path to the
					image location where the <varname>vim</varname> port is
					installed.  If you have more than one version or variants of a
					single port installed, you can specify the version string of
					the port as the last argument, similar to the above examples
					of activation and deactivation.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
