<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="membership">
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>
				committer
			</keyword>
			<keyword>
				
			</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>MacPorts membership</title> 
	<sect1>
		<title>Becoming a MacPorts committer</title>

		<para>Becoming a member of the MacPorts project with commit access
		to our Subversion repository is pretty much a matter of involvement in any of
		the areas of the project and the record you can establish thereof. We
		encourage any developer and/or volunteer to apply for a Subversion account
		if certain simple requirements are met:</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry id='list'>
				<term>
					Involvement on the List:
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>One key attribute of any MacPorts committer must be
					enthusiasm for the project, so therefore we appreciate applicants
					who've shown their involvement through active participation
					on the <ulink
                    url="http://lists.macosforge.org/mailman/listinfo/macports-users">main user list</ulink>,
					either through general user support and/or project roadmap discussion
					and brainstorming.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry id='contributions'>
				<term>
					Contribution record:
				</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>If applying for access to the "mports" section of the project,
					an established record as a maintainer of already existing ports is
					preferable. This can be accomplished either through the inheritance
					of abandoned ports (those with the sole nomaintainer [at] macports DOT org
					maintainer address) or through writing your own from scratch. If instead
					you plan to apply to any other area of the project, like "base" or "www", contributions
					in the form of patches that can vouch for your skills on the aspects you
					plan to help with are certainly a big plus. In all cases, submissions to
					the project should be processed per the instructions detailed on the
					"<ulink url="/docs/ch15.html">MacPorts Submissions</ulink>" chapter.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>If you feel like you meet and comply with these requirements and wish
		to become a member of the group to help out personally, do feel free to send
		a note to the <ulink href="/docs/ch12s03.html">PortMgr</ulink>
		steering committee explaining your contributions, how long you've been involved
		with the project and why think you'd make a good committer. The sole purpose of
		said forum is overseeing the general evolution of MacPorts, so it is where you
		should turn to for membership requests.</para>

		<para>For a brief listing of the duties &amp; benefits resulting from holding
		an OpenDarwin account, along with a short jump start on Subversion primaries, read
		OpenDarwin's <ulink url="http://opendarwin.org/en/articles/committer_guide/ar01s02.html">Committer's Guide</ulink>
		for account applicants. The MacPorts' specific <ulink url="http://trac.macports.org/projects/macports/wiki/NewCommittersGuide">New Committer's Guide</ulink>
		is also a must read for new comers to become acquainted with our own procedures
		and guidelines.</para>

	</sect1>
</chapter>
